AND GOOD AFTERNOON AND WELCOME TO THE NOVEMBER FOURTH, 2025
REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT TEN MEMBERS ARE
PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA ALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE
ROMITA MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE
BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE ROMITA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY
AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT
STANDS UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR
ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THIS BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
ESPECIALLY JAMES KAWANA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO
ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE
CHAMBER. WE'RE IN ROOM 250 ON THE SECOND
FLOOR IN CITY HALL. WHEN YOU CANNOT BE HERE WE ARE
SHOWING OR AIRING THE PROCEEDINGS LIVE ON AS OF G OF
TV CHANNEL 26. OR YOU MAY VIEW THE LIVE STREAM
AT W W W DOT AS OF G OF TV.ORG. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT
YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT IN WRITING.
YOU CAN EITHER SEND AN EMAIL TO BE OFFSET AS HAVE GOV DAWG OR
VIA THE US POSTAL SERVICE. JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244
SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102. IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A FUTURE
REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITY
ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. THANK YOU MEMBERS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. >> APPROVAL OF THE SEPTEMBER
30TH 2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES .
COLLEAGUES, CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED MOVED BY WALTON SECONDED BY CHAN.
MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR OUTFIELDER FIELDER
EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM ONE ITEM ONE
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 5.8
MILLION TO FUND AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECTS TO THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND TO PLACE THESE
FUNDS ON CONTROLLERS RESERVE PENDING THE SALE OF THE TAX
INCREMENT REVENUE BONDS AND RECEIPT OF PROCEEDS
IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM ONE SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MUHAMMAD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM TWO ITEM TWO THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODE TO REVISE THE HEALTHY AIRPORT
ORDINANCE TO REQUIRE BEGINNING ON JANUARY 1ST, 2027 THAT THE
CONTRACTING PARTIES EMPLOYING CERTAIN AIRPORT WORKERS MAKE
IRREVOCABLE HEALTH CARE EXPENDITURES ON BEHALF OF THEIR
EMPLOYEES AT TIERED RATES TO REFLECT THE EMPLOYEES HOUSEHOLD
SIZE COLLEAGUES. >> WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME SAME
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM THREE ITEM THREE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE THE ZONING MAP
CONSOLIDATING THE NORTH BEACH SPECIAL USE AND NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS AND TO EXPAND ALLOWABLE USES AND USE
SIZE LIMITS IN CERTAIN ZONING DISTRICTS.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM THREE SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MY MIND MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MILKER MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SORTER SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON KNOW THERE ARE EIGHT EYES
AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS CHAN AND WALTON VOTING NO THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
FOR ITEM FOUR THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE
HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY TO APPLY
FOR AND ACCEPT THE COUNTY ALLOCATION AWARD UNDER THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TRANSITIONAL HOUSING PROGRAM FOR AN
APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF 4.7 MILLION AND HOUSING NAVIGATION
AND MAINTENANCE PROGRAM FOR APPROXIMATELY 600,000 WHICH
PROVIDES FUNDING TO HELP YOUNG ADULTS SECURE AND MAINTAIN
HOUSING. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
FOR SUPERVISE HER CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MENDELSON
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THEIR ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM FIVE ITEM FIVE RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE THE SIXTH AMENDMENT TO THE INTERNATIONAL TERMINAL
DUTY FREE AND LUXURY STORE LEASE BETWEEN DFS GROUP P
AND THE CITY AND COUNTY TO TEMPORARILY REDUCE PERCENTAGE
RENT TO 28% OF GROSS REVENUES UP TO 100,000,032% FOR GROSS
REVENUES ABOVE 100 MILLION FOR LEASE YEARS 2026 THROUGH 2029
AND TO APPROVE A TEMPORARY REDUCTION IN THE MAG THE
MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE FOR THE SAME DURATION BY
ESTABLISHING THE MAG AT 25 MILLION FOR 2026 WITH ANNUAL
ADJUSTMENTS AS PROVIDED IN THE LEASE.
>> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM SIX. ITEM SIX THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE AN AGREEMENT WITH COMPLETE COACH WORKS TO PERFORM
MIDLIFE OVERHAUL SERVICES TO REPLACE AND REHABILITATE
SYSTEMS FOR UP TO 152 STANDARD AND 69 ARTICULATED HYBRID
ELECTRIC NEW FLIER COACHES FOR 95.4 MILLION FOR A FIVE YEAR
INITIAL TERM WITH TO ONE YEAR OPTIONS TO EXTEND AND WE CAN
TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN RESOLUTION TO EXEMPT FROM THE
COMPETITIVE BIDDING POLICY SET FORTH IN THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE SECTIONS 2.6-1 AND 23.33 AND TO APPROVE A PORT LEASE
17322 FOR THE CONTINUED OPERATION OF AN OBSERVATION
WHEEL AT SEAWALL LOT 301 BETWEEN THE PORT OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND SKY STAR WHEEL LLC FOR AN 18 MONTH TERM WITH
ONE OPTION TO EXTEND FOR 18 MONTHS THROUGH APRIL 30TH 2027
FOR A MONTHLY BASE RENT OF 11,000 WITH AN ANNUAL INCREASE
PLUS A PERCENTAGE RENT OF 8% FOR AN ESTIMATED REVENUE OF
APPROXIMATE ONLY 1.8 MILLION AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS AND WE CAN TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PLANNING CODE TO ESTABLISH A PROCESS FOR THE CONVERSION OF
CERTAIN MEDICAL CANNABIS DISPENSARIES TO CANNABIS RETAIL
ESTABLISHMENTS AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER NINE ITEM NINE THIS IS
AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE AND THE PLANNING CODE TO CLARIFY DEADLINES FOR APPEALS
OF DECISIONS OR DETERMINATIONS BY THE ZONING ADMINISTRATOR TO
AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL OUT TO NUMBER TEN ITEM TEN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE IN THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO MODIFY THE STATE THE CITY'S STATE MANDATED
ADU THE ACCESSORY DWELLING UNIT APPROVAL PROCESS AND TO CONFORM
CHANGES TO STATE ADU LAW TO INCLUDE BY REMOVING ANY APPEAL
TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS AND TO INCREASE SIZE LIMITS FOR
CERTAIN DETACHED NEW CONSTRUCTION TO USE ON A LOT
CONTAINING A SINGLE FAMILY DWELLING TO AFFIRM THE SECOND
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 11 ITEM 11 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE TO ELIMINATE THE REQUIREMENT FOR A CONTRACTOR
PARKING PLAN AS A CONDITION PRECEDENT FOR APPROVAL OF
EXCAVATION PERMITS FOR MAJOR WORK THAT IS 30 CONSECUTIVE
CALENDAR DAYS OR LONGER AND AS A CONDITION PRECEDENT OF
SPECIFIED TEMPORARY STREETS SPACE OCCUPANCY PERMITS FOR
CONSTRUCTION WORK AS WELL AS THE ASSOCIATED PARKING PLAN
NOTICE REQUIREMENT AND THE PARKING PLAN REVIEW
AND INSPECTION FEES AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 12 ITEM 12 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO STREAMLINE THE REQUIREMENTS AND APPROVAL
PROCESSES FOR THE COMMEMORATIVE DESIGNATION OF PUBLIC RIGHT OF
WAY AND PUBLIC PLACES AND THE INSTALLATION OF COMMEMORATIVE
STREET PLAQUES TO HONOR CITES EVENTS AND PERSONS OF
HISTORICAL INTEREST OR SIGNIFICANCE TO SAN FRANCISCO
TO ELIMINATE THE REQUIREMENT THAT PUBLIC WORKS HOLD A
HEARING ON APPLICATIONS FOR A COMMEMORATIVE STREET PLAQUE
AND TO AFFIRM THE SPEAKER DETERMINATION SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 13 ITEM 13 ITEM 13 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
TO DETERMINE THE CIRCUMSTANCES UNDER WHICH CONTRACTORS
PERFORMING EXCAVATION IN THE PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY SHALL BE
REQUIRED TO OBTAIN POLLUTION LIABILITY INSURANCE AND TO
AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAME
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 14 THROUGH 20 TOGETHER ITEMS 14
THROUGH 20 ARE SEVEN ORDINANCES THAT REPEAL OR AMEND THE
FOLLOWING CODES IN THEIR ENTIRETY FOR ITEM 14.
THIS REPEALS THE 2022 PLUMBING CODE AND ENACTS A 2025 PLUMBING
CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA PLUMBING CODE AS
AMENDED BY SAN FRANCISCO TO ADOPT THE ENVIRONMENTAL
FINDINGS AND FINDINGS OF LOCAL CONDITIONS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE ITEM 15 THIS REPEALS THE 2022
MECHANICAL CODE AND ENACTS A 2025 MECHANICAL CODE TO CONSIST
OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA MECHANICAL CODE AS AMENDED BY
SAN FRANCISCO TO ADOPT ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS
AND FINDINGS OF LOCAL CONDITIONS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE FOR ITEM 16.
THIS REPEALS THE 2022 ELECTRICAL CODE AND ENACTS A
2025 ELECTRICAL CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA
ELECTRICAL CODE AS AMENDED BY SAN FRANCISCO ITEM 17 THIS
REPEALS THE 2022 GREEN BUILDING CODE AND ENACTS A 2025 GREEN
BUILDING CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA GREEN BUILDING
STANDARDS CODE AS AMENDED BY SAN FRANCISCO TO ADOPT THE
ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS OF LOCAL CONDITIONS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE AND THE FINDINGS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
PUBLIC RESOURCES CODE ITEM 18 THIS ORDINANCE REPEALS THE 2022
EXISTING BUILDING CODE AND ENACTS A 2025 EXISTING
BUILDING CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA EXISTING
BUILDING CODE AS AMENDED BY SAN FRANCISCO TO ADOPT THE
ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS AND FINDINGS OF LOCAL
CONDITIONS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE.
ITEM 19 REPEALS THE 2022 BUILDING CODE AND ENACTS A 2025
BUILDING CODE TO CONSIST OF THE 2025 CALIFORNIA BUILDING CODE
AND THE 2025 CALIFORNIA RESIDENTIAL CODE AS AMENDED BY
SAN FRANCISCO TO ADOPT THE ENVIRONMENTAL FINDINGS
AND FINDINGS OF LOCAL CONDITIONS UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE AND FOR ITEM 20 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS
THE HOUSING CODE TO UPDATE REFERENCES TO PROVISIONS OF THE
2025 BUILDING INSPECTION CODE AND TO AFFIRM THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT AND FOR ALL ITEMS 14 THROUGH 22
PROVIDE AN OPERATIVE DATE AS OF JANUARY 1ST 2020 SIX AND I
THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 21 ITEM 21 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO REQUIRE THE ARTS COMMISSION
TO DEVELOP AND ADMINISTER A CERTIFICATION PROCESS TO
IDENTIFY ARTISTS IN SAN FRANCISCO WHO MAY BE ELIGIBLE
FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING COLLEAGUES THIS ITEM PASSED OUT
OF THE RULES COMMITTEE WITH POSITIVE RECOMMENDATION ON
OCTOBER 27TH. THANK YOU CHAIR WALTON
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> THE LEGISLATION WOULD
ESTABLISH AS THE CLERK INDICATED, AN ARTIST HOUSING
CERTIFICATION PROGRAM UNDER THE ARTS COMMISSION TO FACILITATE
ARTIST HOUSING PROJECTS. THERE'S ONE CURRENTLY
IN CONTEMPLATION WE HOPE COMING TO FRUITION SOON AND SUPERVISOR
DORSEY'S DISTRICT BUT WE HOPE THERE WILL BE MANY MORE.
I HAVE MY OFFICE HAS PREVIOUSLY CIRCULATED BY EMAIL A FEW NON
SUBSTANTIVE AMENDMENTS AND I HAVE GIVEN THEM OUT EARLIER.
IN GENERAL THESE WILL MAKE A FEW MINOR EDITS TO THE FINDINGS
FOR CLEANUP AND ACCURACY PROVIDE THAT THE DIRECTOR OF
THE ARTS COMMISSION WILL HAVE THE AUTHORITY TO DIRECT THE
APPLICATION PROCESS FOR THE CERTIFICATION, ADD A
RECONSIDERATION PROCESS FOR APPLICANTS WHO MAY BE REJECTED
AND LASTLY SUNSET OR CLEAN UP THE SUNSET AND OPERATIVE DATES
. AGAIN THESE ARE NON SUBSTANTIVE
. DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSSI
IS NODDING ON THAT POINT. >> CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO ADOPT
THESE AMENDMENTS SO MOVE. >> DORSEY SECONDED BY CHERYL
AND COLLEAGUES CAN WE TAKE THAT THOSE AMENDMENTS WITHOUT
OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE AMENDMENTS ARE ADOPTED.
AND THEN COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20
TWO ITEM 22 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO EXEMPT THE HEALTH
SERVICE SYSTEM'S LIFE AND LONG TERM DISABILITY INSURANCE
SERVICES CONTRACT FROM THE REQUIREMENTS OF ARTICLE 111 THE
MINIMUM COMPENSATION AND ARTICLE 121 THE HEALTH CARE
ACCOUNTABILITY OF THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT CODES MADAM
CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 22.
>> SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY ABSENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
ABSENCE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD OTHERS HERE FEEL THERE WAS AN
EYE ON ME. >> OF COURSE YOU ARE.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER OR FIELDER
I. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MILKER
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WILTON I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 23 ITEM 20 THREE THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT THOMAS JAMES
ROCHA TO THE HOMELESSNESS OVERSIGHT COMMISSION TERM
ENDING MAY 1ST 2029 MADAM CLERK ,CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THIS
ITEM ON ITEM 23 SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD NO
SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN I MANDEL MAN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND TWO
NOSE WITH FIELDER AND MAHMOOD VOTING NO THE MOTION IS
APPROVED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 24 AND 25 TOGETHER
ITEMS 24 AND 25 ARE TWO MOTIONS TO APPROVE THE MAYOR'S
APPOINTMENTS TO THE HOMELESSNESS OVERSIGHT
COMMISSION. >> ITEM 24 APPROVES OH BY RAMBO
TERM ENDING MAY 1ST 2027 AND ITEM 25 APPROVES DAWN TABLE
TERM ENDING MAY 1ST 2029 PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THESE ITEMS ON
ITEMS 24 AND 25 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN ALL
RIGHT GENTLEMEN. EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
EYES SUPERVISOR SADR. SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTZ AND I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTIONS ARE APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK
LET'S GO TO OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS ITEM 28 WAS NOT
FORWARDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT SO PLEASE CALL ITEM 29.
>> YES, ALTHOUGH ITEM 28 IS MUTED AS THE PRESIDENT STATED
ITEM 28 AND 29 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
NOVEMBER 3RD. ITEM 29 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO REQUIRE CERTAIN PLANNING
DEPARTMENT FEES TO BE PAID TO THE DEPARTMENT AT THE TIME THE
DEVELOPMENT APPLICATION IS SUBMITTED TO MODIFY THE
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW FEES FOR LARGE PROJECTS AND TO REMOVE
THE SEPARATE FEE SCHEDULE FOR CLASS 32 CATEGORICAL EXEMPTIONS
UNDER THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT TO
AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER 30. >> ITEM 30 WAS CONSIDERED BY
THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
NOVEMBER 3RD. IT WAS RECOMMENDED AS A
COMMITTEE REPORT AS AMENDED WITH A NEW TITLE ITEM 30 NOW
APPROVES THE APPOINTMENT. THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE
PRESIDENT RAFAEL MANDEL MIN'S NOMINATION FOR THE APPOINTMENT
OF JUDY LEE TO THE BUILDING INSPECTION COMMISSION TERM
ENDING JULY 1ST, 2027. >> AND LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION
IS APPROVED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL
CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS. FIRST MEMBER TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS SUPERVISOR CHAN SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A LETTER OF
INQUIRY TO THE DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES ON THE POLICIES
THE POLICIES AND PROCEDURES IN PLACE FOR WHEN A CITY
EMPLOYEES EXPERIENCES SEXUAL ASSAULTS OR HARASSMENT IN THE
WORKPLACE. SAN FRANCISCO HAS A LONG STATED
HISTORY OF SUPPORTING SURVIVORS OF SEXUAL ASSAULTS
AND HARASSMENT. IN 2018 SUPERVISOR RON
AND PASSED IT LEGISLATION CREATING THE OFFICE OF SEXUAL
HARASSMENT AND ASSAULT RESPONSE AND PREVENTION TO HELP
SURVIVORS NAVIGATE A CITY'S AND RESOURCES AFTER AN ASSAULT
OR HARASSMENT OR OCCUR IN 2022 ASSEMBLY MEMBERS STEPHANIE
CHAMPIONED A BALLOT MEASURE ESTABLISHING THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
FOR VICTIMS RIGHTS. WE KNOW THAT SEXUAL ASSAULT
AND SEXUAL HARASSMENT ARE DEEPLY PERVASIVE.
THEY IMPACT MULTIPLE GENERATIONS OF FAMILIES AND ARE
BOTH OFTENTIMES INVISIBLE AND SEVERELY UNDERREPORTED AS A
CITY WHEN WHAT A DEMONSTRATOR HISTORY OF STANDING UP OFFICERS
TASKED IT WITH SUPPORTING SURVIVORS AFTER AN ASSAULT OR
ALL HARASSMENT OCCURS I WANT TO BETTER UNDERSTAND THE PROTOCOLS
AND POLICIES IMPLEMENTED BY THE CITY DEPARTMENTS FOR IF WHEN A
CITY EMPLOYEE EXPERIENCES ASSAULTS OR HARASSMENT IN THE
WORKPLACE I WANT TO ENSURE THAT WE HAVE UP TO DATE
AND CULTURALLY COMPETENT BEST PRACTICES IN PLACE AND THEREBY
SAY SOMETHING. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SIR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK I'M COLLEAGUES I AM TODAY NOTIFYING THE HEADS OF 41
CITY DEPARTMENTS OF MY INTENT TO SUBMIT LETTERS OF INQUIRY
THROUGH THE OFFICE OF THE BOARD CLERK OF COURSE REQUESTING THAT
THEY ESTIMATE THE AMOUNT OF TIME AND STAFF RESOURCES THEIR
DEPARTMENTS HAVE DEVOTED TO COMPLYING WITH OUR SURVEILLANCE
TECHNOLOGY ORDINANCE. I WILL ASK THAT THIS BE
ESTIMATED ON AN ANNUAL BASIS SINCE ITS ENACTMENT IN 2019
MANY SAN FRANCISCANS WILL RECALL THAT THIS ORDINANCE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 19 BE ACQUISITION OF SURVEILLANCE
TECHNOLOGY PLACED RESTRICTIONS ON THE USE OF FACIAL
RECOGNITION TECHNOLOGY. FAR LESS WELL KNOWN, HOWEVER,
WAS THAT IT ALSO IMPOSED SIGNIFICANT RESEARCH REPORTING
OVERSIGHT AND ITERATIVE ENGAGEMENT BURDENS ON CITY
AGENCIES ORIGINALLY ENACTED IN JUNE OF 2019 THIS 12,500
WORD 22 PAGE ORDINANCE ORIGINALLY PRESCRIBED A
DETAILED PROCESS REQUIRING CITY DEPARTMENTS TO SUBMIT AN
INVENTORY OF ALL SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGIES TO THE COMMITTEE
ON INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY OR QUOTE IN ITS FOUR PERSON
WORKFORCE FOR EACH SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGY DEPARTMENTS ARE
REQUIRED TO SUBMIT A SURVEILLANCE IMPACT REPORT, A
SURVEILLANCE POLICY AND ANNUAL SURVEILLANCE REPORTS WHICH HAS
SINCE BEEN UPDATED TO BE BIANNUAL SURVEILLANCE REPORTS.
THE ORDINANCE IS LABYRINTHINE APPROVAL PROCESS BEGINS WITH A
COURT SUBCOMMITTEE WHERE SUBMISSIONS ARE SCRUTINIZED BY
AT LEAST ONE MEETING OF THE PRIVACY SURVEILLANCE ADVISORY
BOARD OR PIECE OF COIN ITSELF THEN REVIEWED THE SUBMISSIONS
UNTIL SUBSEQUENT LEGISLATION REMOVED THAT STEP AND THEN THE
SUBMISSIONS ARE SENT TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR OUR
APPROVAL. COLLEAGUES MAY RECALL THAT I
RECENTLY PROPOSED AN AMENDMENT TO REPEAL A SINGLE SENTENCE
FROM THIS ORDINANCE TO REMOVE THE ORDINANCES PREVAILING
PLAINTIFFS FEES AND COSTS PROVISION WHICH I CONSIDER TO
BE A DISSERVICE TO OUR TAXPAYERS AND FRANKLY A
BRAZENLY SELF-DEALING SOP TO ADVOCACY ORGANIZATIONS WHO SUE
MUNICIPALITIES. HOWEVER, IT WAS BROUGHT TO MY
ATTENTION THAT ATTORNEYS FEES AND COSTS MAY ONLY BE A DROP
IN THE BUCKET COMPARED TO THE VASTLY LARGER INVESTMENT OF
TIME IN TAXPAYER FUNDED RESOURCES FOR CITY AGENCIES TO
COMPLY WITH THIS ORDINANCE. THIS LETTER THESE LETTERS OF
INCREASE WILL GO TO 27 DISTINCT DEPARTMENTS WITH APPLICABLE
SURVEILLANCE TECHNOLOGIES. ANOTHER 12 DEPARTMENTS THAT ARE
COVERED UNDER THE CITYWIDE SOCIAL MEDIA MONITORING
SOFTWARE POLICY AND ALSO THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE
AND COURT FOR THEIR ESTIMATIONS OF STAFF TIME AND RESOURCES.
THAT ADMIN CODE 19 BE COMPLIANCE AS IMPOSED ON THEIR
OFFICERS AT A TIME WHEN SO MANY CONSCIENTIOUS ACTIVISTS
AND LEADERS ARE DOING MUCH NEEDED WORK TO IMPROVE
EFFICIENCIES AND CUT NEEDLESS WASTE IN SAN FRANCISCO'S LOCAL
GOVERNMENT ON COMMISSION STREAMLINING ON CONTRACTING
REFORM ON CHARTER REFORM AND MORE.
I THINK WE ARE ALL BEST SERVED BY AN ESTIMATION OF COSTS
IMPOSED BY A LAW THAT ALSO HAS IMPORTANT IMPLICATIONS FOR
PUBLIC SAFETY AND EFFECTIVE POLICING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH THE CLERK AND DEPARTMENT HEADS
AS WE GATHER DATA TO BETTER INFORM POLICY DECISIONS WHICH
WILL HOPEFULLY MAKE LOCAL GOVERNMENT MORE COST EFFECTIVE
AND OUR CITY SAFER AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY MADAM CLERK,
LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES IT'S NOW TIME FOR THE 230 SPECIAL ORDER WHICH IS TO
HONOR THOSE RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR MERITORIOUS
SERVICE. ALL RIGHT.
AND FIRST UP, DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL COLLEAGUES
TODAY I AM VERY, VERY HONORED TO COMMEND CHO CHANG YAO ON
THE OCCASION OF HER 107TH BIRTHDAY LATER THIS YEAR.
A REMARKABLE MILESTONE THAT REFLECTS A LEGACY THAT REFLECTS
A LIFE OF STRENGTH, OF PERSEVERANCE AND OF FAMILY.
NOW I'M NOT SURE I CAN SAY THAT YOU ARE NECESSARILY THE OLDEST
LIVING SAN FRANCISCAN TODAY BUT YOU'RE THE OLDEST LIVING THAT I
KNOW OF AND FOR THAT I AM VERY HAPPY.
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY WE ARE HERE TO CELEBRATE NOT ONLY YOU
BUT YOUR LEGACY OF FAMILY. AND I'LL TALK ABOUT THAT IN A
MINUTE. BUT FOR YOU I JUST WANT YOU TO
KNOW HOW MUCH YOUR FAMILY HAS MEANT TO ME AND TO SO MANY
OTHERS ON A PERSONAL LEVEL. BUT LET'S TALK ABOUT YOU FOR A
MINUTE. >> CHO CHANG YAO HOON WAS BORN
IN HONOLULU, HAWAII ON JUNE 9TH, 1918, THE FOURTH OF NINE
SIBLINGS. NOW I FOUND THIS INTERESTING
YOUR BIRTH CERTIFICATE ONLY HAS FOUR DIGITS.
AND NOW HAWAII USES TEN. WHEN YOU WERE JUST TWO YEARS
OLD, HER FAMILY RETURNED TO CHINA AS HER FATHER JOINED DR.
SUN YAT SEN'S REVOLUTION A POWERFUL CONNECTION TO HISTORY
IN ITSELF. IN HER YOUTH SHE WAS CROWNED
ONE OF THE FOUR BEAUTY QUEENS. NO SURPRISE THERE OF THE KEY
DISTRICT IN ZHONGSHAN CITY, GUANGDONG.
AND AT AGE 20 SHE WAS WOOED BY DR. CHO LONG CHUNG, THE
DIRECTOR OF CANTON HOSPITAL WHO LATER BECAME HER HUSBAND.
TOGETHER THEY BUILT A BEAUTIFUL LIFE IN MACAO RAISING SEVEN
CHILDREN AND LATER BECOMING GRANDPARENTS AND GREAT
GRANDPARENTS MANY TIMES OVER 16 GRAND CHILDREN AND 19 GREAT
GRANDCHILDREN. WITH THE FAMILY CONTINUING TO
GROW. TODAY MRS. CHOOSE, ONE OF THE
OLDEST LIVING RESIDENTS IN SAN FRANCISCO IN HER LIFE IS THAT
TESTAMENT TO LOVE, TO RESILIENCE AND THE ENDURING
SPIRIT OF FAMILY. HER LEGACY LIVES ON NOT ONLY
THROUGH HER MANY DESCENDANTS BUT ALSO THROUGH HER
GRANDDAUGHTER LESLIE HIEU, WHO FOUNDED PIERCE'S PLEDGE
IN HONOR OF HER LATE SON PIERCE.
LESLIE UNFORTUNATELY COULDN'T BE HERE TODAY BUT IS
REPRESENTED BY HER PARENTS TERESA AND HOWARD.
HUGH, WHO FOUND LESLIE HAS TRANSFORMED UNIMAGINABLE LOSS
INTO ADVOCACY WORKING TO PREVENT FAMILY VIOLENCE
AND PROMOTE FIREARMS SAFETY REFORMS SO THAT OTHER FAMILIES
MAY NEVER FACE THE SAME TRAGEDY NOW THAT COURAGE, THAT
COMPASSION THAT DEFINED LESLIE'S WORK ARE A REFLECTION
OF THE SAME STRENGTH THAT HAS CARRIED MRS. CHIU THROUGH MORE
THAN A CENTURY OF LIFE THAT LIFE OF PURPOSE, THAT LIFE OF
LOVE, THAT LIFE OF FAMILY ACROSS GENERATIONS.
SO TODAY WE CELEBRATE YOU CHOOSING YOUR ONE FOR YOUR
LONGEVITY BUT REALLY FOR YOUR FAMILY'S LEGACY OF SERVICE
AND FOR THE LIGHT THAT SO MANY MEMBERS OF YOUR FAMILY HAVE
TOLD ME THAT YOU BRING TO THEM AND TO EVERYONE IN OUR CITY.
SO TO YOU, MRS. CHIU AND TO YOUR ENTIRE FAMILY.
CONGRATULATIONS ON THIS EXTRAORDINARY MILESTONE.
WE WISH YOU CONTINUED HEALTH, JOY AND THE BLESSINGS OF FAMILY
FOR MANY YEARS TO COME. AND NOW I INVITE TRES TO SAY A
FEW WORDS BE IT SHERPAS AND A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISOR THAT YOU AND FOR CHANG FAMILIES ARE DEEPLY
HONORED TO BE HERE TODAY AS A SUPERVISOR.
SHARA SAY HE TOLD HIS FRIEND STORY OF MY MOTHER I NEED TO
IMPROVISE SOMETHING THAT MY MOTHER IS A VERY STRONG WILLED
AND VERY PROUD WOMAN AND THAT'S THE QUALITIES THAT USUALLY HELP
BUT ARE ASKED TO BECOME THE LIFE OF AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
OF 107 YEARS OLD FOUR MONTHS AND FOUR DAYS TWO DAYS WHERE
SHOULD 630 9230 DAYS TODAY? >> OKAY WE ARE VERY DELIGHTED
THAT NO FAMILY IS REPRESENTED HERE TODAY BY FOUR GENERATION
OF US. >> OUR WHOLE FAMILY AND ALSO
EXTENDED FAMILY. >> UNFORTUNATELY HER YOUNGER
SISTERS AND KIMBERLY WHO IS 98 YEARS OLD AND AUNTIE LUCY 97
ARE UNABLE TO JOIN HER HERE TODAY ON BEHALF OF MY MOTHER,
THE CHU AND THE CHANG FAMILY HAVE A SPECIAL APPRECIATION TO
SUPERVISOR CHARO. WE EXTEND OUR HEARTFELT
GRATITUDE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISOR FOR
RECOGNIZING MY MOTHER AS THE OLDEST LIVING PERSON IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
IT IS YOU I 30 TO HAVE YOUR
ALL RIGHT DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SORTER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT THAT WAS REMARKABLE COLLEAGUES TODAY FOR MY
COMMENDATION I AM EXCITED TO HONOR THE INDIVIDUALS WHO
HELPED MAKE DISTRICT THREE'S NEIGHBORHOOD CLEANUPS POSSIBLE.
SO WITH THE DISTRICT THREE CLEANUP CAPTAIN, PLEASE COME ON
UP TO THE PODIUM EVERY WEEKEND THESE DEDICATED VOLUNTEERS
GATHER THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS AND FAN OUT ACROSS OUR STREETS
AND SIDEWALKS TO TACKLE TRASH. >> THEY DON FASHIONABLE ORANGE
VESTS. SOME OF THEM EVEN HAVE THEM
TODAY. THEY GRAB PICKERS AND BROOMS
AND THEY CAREFULLY CONSIDER HOW MANY EXTRA TRASH BAGS TO CARRY
AS BACKUP. THEY EQUIPPED THEMSELVES TO
TACKLE ANY MESS THAT THEY FIND WHETHER IT'S CIGARET BUTTS ON
POLK STREET, PIZZA WRAPPERS ON COLUMBUS AVENUE LEAVES ON
RUSSIAN HILL CARDBOARD IN CHINATOWN THEY PUT IT ALL
IN THE TRASH BAGS AND ONE BY ONE WEEK BY WEEK THEY TAKE
THOUSANDS OF BAGS OF TRASH OFF OUR STREETS.
>> IN FACT, WE AS A GROUP JUST COLLECTED MORE TRASH WHEN I
INVITED THESE FOLKS TO COME IN TODAY'S MEETING FOR A
COMMENDATION TO RECOGNIZE THEM, THEY SAID WELL WHY DON'T WE DO
A CLEAN UP ON THE WAY THEY WANTED TO DO EVEN MORE WORK.
SO WE JUST FINISHED OUR CLEAN UP.
WE STARTED AT PORTSMOUTH SQUARE IN CHINATOWN AND PICKED UP
TRASH AND FILLED MORE BAGS ALL THE WAY TO CITY HALL.
TODAY THESE CLEANUP CAPTAINS OF COURSE ARE NOT PAID.
>> THEY GIVE UP SATURDAY AND SUNDAY MORNINGS.
THEY OFTEN HAVE TO LUG EQUIPMENT, MANY BLOCKS STORE
THINGS IN THEIR OWN GARAGES OR APARTMENTS.
BUT THEY DO IT ALL BECAUSE THEY KNOW THEY'RE MAKING OUR CITY
CLEANER AND MAYBE EVEN MORE IMPORTANTLY THEY ARE BUILDING
COMMUNITY ONE ORANGE TRASH BAG AT A TIME WITH THEIR NEIGHBORS
. WE HAVE A NUMBER OF OUR CLEAN
UP CLEANUPS REPRESENTED TODAY. I WANT TO GIVE OUT PARTICULAR
SHOUT OUTS TO OUR LEADER, OUR CLEANUP LEADER IN CHINATOWN,
JESSICA LEE. OUR LOWER HILL CLEANUP
CAPTAIN, OUR LOWER HILL CLEANUP CAPTAIN DALLAS HYATT
AND DALLAS IS MULTI FACETED IN HIS TALENTS.
>> HE HAS A ART SHOW HIS PHOTOGRAPHY IS IN DISPLAY
IN OUR DISTRICT THREE OFFICE AT THE MOMENT AND HE PICKS UP
TRASH IN THE WEEKEND SO HE DOES IT ALL.
NORTH BEACH IS REPRESENTED BY ERIC BAUER, DEBBIE MARKEY
AND WE HAVE UPPER POLK, LAURA PALIN WE HAVE KUMAR FROM LOWER
POLK. AND I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE
ALTHOUGH THEY COULDN'T MAKE IT WE OF COURSE HAVE REGULAR
CONSISTENT CLEANUPS IN D3 AT THE FILBERT STEPS AND AT
RUSSIAN HILL AS WELL. ALONGSIDE THESE DEDICATED
VOLUNTEERS ARE A SUPPORT SYSTEM THAT MAKE THIS ALL POSSIBLE.
THAT INCLUDES VINCE, YOU AND THE HEAD OF REFUSE REFUSE
VINCE HE HAS SPAWNED COUNTLESS CLEANUPS ACROSS THE CITY AND IS
IN EVERY SINGLE DISTRICT. >> CALEB FROM CIVIC JOY FUND
WHO HELPS HELPS GIVE A LITTLE EXTRA INCENTIVE WITH SOME
LUNCHES AND BREAKFAST AT SOME OF THE CLEANUPS WHICH ALSO
HELPS SUPPORT THE NEARBY SMALL BUSINESSES.
AND THEN OF COURSE BEHIND ALL OF THIS AND IN TANDEM IS IS DPW
AND THE AMAZING WORKERS WHO ARE CLEAN OUT CLEANING UP THE BAGS
OF TRASH AS WELL. >> THESE CLEANUPS WILL ALWAYS
BE NEAR AND DEAR TO MY HEART BECAUSE WHEN I GOT INVOLVED
IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION IN NORTH BEACH MORE THAN TEN
YEARS AGO, I STARTED A REGULAR CLEANUP.
ERIC AND DEBBIE HAVE TAKEN THAT TO NEW HEIGHTS.
WE HAVE A NEW TRADITION AS WELL WHICH I REALLY CHERISH HELPING
TO START WHICH IS A I THINK WE CALL IT THE GREAT NEIGHBORHOOD
TRASH OFF BETWEEN RUSSIAN HILL NEIGHBORS AND NORTH BEACH
NEIGHBORS THOSE TWO NEIGHBORHOODS.
ERIC DEBBIE WE NEED TO KEEP STEPPING IT UP TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE'RE REPRESENTED AND TAKE THE AWARDS NEXT YEAR BUT
DISTRICT THREE CLEANUP CAPTAINS, EVERYONE WHO IS OUT
THERE EVERY SINGLE WEEKEND IT'S TRULY INCREDIBLE WHAT YOU DO.
DALLAS EVERY SINGLE WEEKEND I SEE YOUR LOWER HILL CLEANUPS
GROW. YOU POST THE PICTURES AND YOU
KNOW IT WAS 30 AND THEN IT'S 40 AND THEN IT'S 50.
YOU'RE ALL DOING AMAZING WORK IN YOUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO FOR THIS CITY AND IF ANYONE IS
SO INCLINED TO JOIN TO SPEAK PLEASE DO.
>> AND HI EVERYONE VINCENT FROM REFUSE REFUSE AND THANK YOU
DANNY FOR YOUR LONG TIME FOR SUPPORT OF THIS EVEN PRIOR TO
BEING HERE IN THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND IT JUST GOES TO
SHOW YOU KNOW WHAT ORDINARY CITIZENS CAN DO WHEN WE ACT
COLLECTIVELY AND THE DIFFERENCE THAT WE CAN MAKE AND THESE
PEOPLE BEHIND ME ARE EXTRAORDINARY.
THEY GO ABOVE AND BEYOND ON THEIR OWN TIME AND THEIR OWN
DIME TO BE OUT HERE TO TO LEAD THEIR NEIGHBORS IN THESE
CLEANUPS. AND THEY'RE AGAIN VERY, VERY
EFFECTIVE. NOW THOUGH, WE'RE TACKLING THE
SYMPTOMS OF ALL THE WASTE AND LITTER OUT THERE AND IT
DOES MAKE A HUGE DIFFERENCE. WE'VE SEEN TRANSFORMATIONS
IN THESE AREAS THAT WE HAVE REGULAR CLEANUPS.
IT'S STILL NOT ENOUGH AND THAT'S WHY WE DO NEED THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HELP AS WELL TO TACKLE THE UPSTREAM
CAUSES OF THIS AND NUMBER ONE IS CIGARET LITTER AND I KNOW
ALL OF YOU HAVE DONE CLEANUPS BECAUSE I'VE DONE CLEANUPS
PERSONALLY WITH EVERY SINGLE BOARD OF SUPERVISOR MEMBER HERE
WHICH I THANK YOU FOR BECAUSE YOU GUYS ARE WALKING THE WALK
AND NOT JUST TALKING THE TALK BUT WE NEED YOUR HELP ON THE
OTHER END AND OBVIOUSLY YOU ALL KNOW BARBARA BELLA AND SHE'S
NOT GOING TO STOP EMAILING YOU UNTIL WE GET SOMETHING DONE.
THANKFULLY WE HAVE THE PATHWAY SANTA CRUZ COUNTY, SANTA CRUZ
AND CAPITOLA EVEN TIBURON, BALTIMORE.
BUT THESE ARE PLACES THAT HAVE BANNED THE SALE OF FILTERED
TOBACCO PRODUCTS AND SAN FRANCISCO'S LEADERS AND THE
ENVIRONMENT SHOULD ALSO FOLLOW THIS PATHWAY AND DO THE SAME.
AND WE HAVE A PLAYBOOK FOR THAT.
SO BARBARA, WE'LL BE FOLLOWING UP WITH YOU ON WAYS THAT YOU
CAN SUPPORT THIS. AND IN ADDITION, JUST KEEP
SPREADING THE MESSAGE TO YOUR OWN CONSTITUENTS IN YOUR
DISTRICTS TO COME OUT TO THE CLEANUPS.
ALL OF YOUR DISTRICTS HAVE NEIGHBORHOOD CLEANUPS AND I
KNOW YOU'VE BEEN SUPPORTIVE BUT DON'T DON'T GIVE UP.
KEEP IT GOING. WE HAD A VOLUNTEER TODAY WHO
CAME FOR THEIR FIRST TIME BECAUSE DANNY SENT OUT THE
EMAIL ABOUT THIS CLEANUP THAT WE DID FROM PORTLAND SQUARE TO
CITY HALL AND DON'T ASSUME THAT PEOPLE IN YOUR DISTRICT KNOW
THAT THESE CLEANUPS EXIST. I WAS JUST DOWN IN BAYVIEW
SUPERVISOR WALTON. WE HAD WHITESIDE OUT THERE
AND IT WAS GREAT COMMUNITY BUILDING AND ALL GOOD PIZZA.
AND IT JUST REMINDS ME OF HOW MUCH WE HAVE MORE TO DO TO
BRING MORE PEOPLE IN THE COMMUNITY IN THE FOLD.
AND AGAIN WE'RE SO THANKFUL THAT PEOPLE LIKE THIS BEHIND ME
ARE ARE REALLY SUPPORTING THESE THE UNKNOWN PHASES.
SO IT'S GREAT TO TO GET SOME RECOGNITION FOR THESE PEOPLE
HERE. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH EVERYONE
. COME ON UP TO THE PODIUM
AND SEE. >> OKAY.
OKAY
. >> DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES AHEAD OF VETERANS
DAY IT'S MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE MR. DOUGLAS JENKINS.
CAN YOU COME UP TO THE PODIUM, PLEASE?
>> MR. JENKINS IS A PROUD VETERAN AND A LIFELONG ADVOCATE
FOR HIS SERVICE HAS STRENGTHENED NOT ONLY OUR
COUNTRY BUT THE VERY HEART OF THE FILLMORE AND NEIGHBORHOODS
ACROSS THE CITY FOR OVER 40 YEARS.
>> MR. JENKINS BEGAN HIS MILITARY CAREER IN THE U.S.
ARMY IN NORTH CAROLINA BEFORE RELOCATING TO THE BAY AREA
IN THE 1980S. HE CONTINUED HIS SERVICE FOR
OVER TWO DECADES IN THE ARMY RESERVES AT THE PRESIDIO
ACHIEVING THE RANK OF STAFF SERGEANT SERVICE AND ADVOCACY
COURSE THROUGH HIS VEINS THROUGH THE 80S AND INTO THE
90S. >> MR. JENKINS STOOD UP AMIDST
THE URBAN RENEWAL AND THE WESTERN TRADITION FIGHTING ON
BEHALF OF THE BLACK COMMUNITY FACING DISPLACEMENT.
>> THAT COURAGE ALONG WITH HIS UNWAVERING DEDICATION TO
COMMUNITY HELPED SHAPE A STRONGER AND MORE UNITED
FILLMORE. >> MR. JENKINS ALSO SERVES AS A
PROUD MEMBER OF NEW LIBERATION PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH WHERE HE
CONTINUES TO NURTURE COMMUNITY AND FAITH THROUGH SERVICE BY
MENTORING YOUNGER GENERATIONS TO ENGAGE WITH OUR LOCAL
GOVERNMENT AND VOLUNTEERING HIS TIME AS A POLL WORKER DURING
ELECTION SEASON WHICH IF YOU HAVEN'T SUBMITTED YOUR BALLOT
FOR THIS NOVEMBER'S ELECTION THERE'S STILL TIME TO DO SO.
>> AT THE BOOKER T WASHINGTON COMMUNITY SERVICE CENTER, MR.
JENKINS IS KNOWN AS A CONNECTOR AND A SOURCE OF JOY.
HIS WARMTH AND HONESTY HAVE MADE HIM A CORNERSTONE OF THE
SENIOR WELLNESS PROGRAM A MEMBER WHO NOT ONLY SHOWS UP
BUT UPLIFTS EVERYONE AROUND HIM.
>> HE'S ALSO A SMALL BUSINESS OWNER WHO HAS BUILT SOMETHING
LASTING FOR 36 YEARS. MR. JENKINS RAN A BRIGHT IMAGE
COSMETIC CENTER IN THE BAYVIEW PROVIDING BEAUTY PRODUCTS
AND ENCOURAGEMENT TO GENERATION OF LOCAL FAMILIES.
WHEN ASKED HIS FRIENDS AT BOOKER T WASHINGTON DESCRIBED
HIM AS A KIND AND GENTLE SOUL SOMEONE WHO WAS ALWAYS
ENERGETIC AND HAPPY. >> THROUGH COLLEAGUES I'D BE
REMISS IF I DIDN'T ALSO SHARE THAT THAT WAS DIRECTLY FOLLOWED
BY DON'T LET THAT FOOL YOU. >> HE'S A STRAIGHT SHOOTER WHO
HAS NO TROUBLE SPEAKING HIS MIND WHEN NEEDED.
>> DOUGLAS JENKINS IS THE EMBODIMENT OF SERVICE NOT JUST
IN UNIFORM BUT IN ACTION. THANK YOU, MR. JENKINS, FOR ALL
YOUR SERVICE. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> GIVE AN HONOR TO GOD FIRST. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS PUT US
IN THE AUDIENCE AND MYSELF JUST GIVEN THANKS TO BOOKER T
COMMUNITY CENTER FOR THE ENJOYMENT THAT I HAVE
ESTABLISHED WITHIN THE LAST COUPLE OF YEARS.
I THINK THAT ALL VETERANS THAT MIGHT BE HERE IN THIS AUDIENCE
MIGHT BE HERE IN THE CITY STATE, COUNTRY IS DESERVING OF
THE DAY. SO VETERANS DAY ACTUALLY IS
OBSERVED THIS COMING MONDAY. I WANT TO ASK THE PEOPLE
IN THIS ROOM TO DO WHATEVER THEY CAN TO ENLIGHTEN THE FACT
THAT YOU'VE BEEN A VETERAN, THAT PERSON BEEN A VETERAN
AND GIVEN THE BENEFIT OF THE DOUBT THAT THEY LOVE THIS
COUNTRY AND LOVED THEMSELVES. >> THANK YOU
SO. >> DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR
DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY PRIVILEGE TO OFFER THIS COMMENDATION FOR
MARIA TAN WHOSE DAUGHTER CAROL TAN WILL BE ACCEPTING ON HER
BEHALF. >> THAT'S GIRL STUFF.
WHAT AN HONOR TO CELEBRATE THE EXTRAORDINARY LIFE OF MARIA TAN
. BORN ON SEPTEMBER 25TH, 1921
IN THE PHILIPPINES TO CHINESE IMMIGRANT PARENTS MARIA CARRIED
WITH HER THE COURAGE AND RESILIENCE OF HER FAMILY'S
JOURNEY. IN 1978 SHE CAME TO THE UNITED
STATES AND LATER PROUDLY BECAME AN AMERICAN CITIZEN.
SINCE 1982, SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN FORTUNATE TO COUNT HER
AMONG ITS OWN RESIDENTS. MARIA STORY WELL REPRESENTS THE
IMMIGRANT EXPERIENCE THAT HAS SO POWERFULLY SHAPED OUR CITY
AND CONTINUES TO SHAPE OUR CITY AS WELL.
IT REFLECTS THE STRENGTH, FAITH AND FAITH AND DETERMINATION
THAT DEFINED THE DIVERSE COMMUNITIES WE SAN FRANCISCANS
CHERISH. FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES,
MARIA DEVOTED HERSELF TO SERVICE THROUGH HER WORK WITH
SELF-HELP FOR THE ELDERLY AND LATER HER MANY VOLUNTEER
HOURS AT THE OLD SAINT MARY'S BOOKSTORE.
SHE HAS TOUCHED COUNTLESS LIVES WITH QUIET AND STEADY KINDNESS.
HER EXAMPLE REMINDS US THAT TRUE COMMUNITY IS BUILT THROUGH
CONSISTENT ACTS OF GENEROSITY AND CARE.
MARIA'S DEDICATION HAS UPLIFTED AND INSPIRED MANY PEOPLE
AND HER OWN LIFE SHOWS THE DIFFERENCE ONE PERSON CAN MAKE
WHEN THEY FOCUS ON HELPING OTHERS.
MARIA'S LIFE HAS ALSO BEEN RICH IN FAMILY JOY AND CREATIVITY
AND HER CATHOLIC FAITH. A DEVOTED PARISHIONER AT OLD
SAINT MARY'S CATHEDRAL, SHE HAS DRAWN STRENGTH AND FORGED
ENDURING FRIENDSHIPS AMONG HER FAITH COMMUNITY.
SHE HAS FOUND PEACE AMONG THE REDWOODS OF MUIR WOODS AND HAS
SHARED HER LOVE OF POETRY BY READING AND WRITING, OFFERING
BEAUTY AND INSIGHT TO THOSE AROUND HER.
THESE PASSIONS HAVE ENRICHED NOT ONLY HER OWN LIFE BUT HAVE
ALSO BEEN GIFTS TO HER FAMILY, HER FRIENDS AND HER NEIGHBORS.
ABOVE ALL, MARIA'S LEGACY SHINES THROUGH HER FAMILY.
AS A DEVOTED MOTHER OF FOUR. SHE HAS PASSED DOWN THE VALUES
OF LOVE, PERSEVERANCE AND FAITH THAT WILL ENDURE FOR MANY
GENERATIONS TO COME. TODAY AS WE HONOR HER, WE
CELEBRATE HER LIFE'S MILESTONES AND THE LASTING CONTRIBUTIONS
SHE HAS MADE TO THE STRENGTH AND CAREER CHARACTER OF SAN
FRANCISCO. AT THE AGE OF 104 NOTABLY
NEITHER THE OLDEST LIVING SAN FRANCISCO NOR EVEN THE OLDEST
HONOREE TODAY MARIA TAN REMINDS US WHAT IT MEANS TO LIVE WITH
PURPOSE. WHILE SHE IS UNABLE TO ACCEPT
THIS COMMENDATION IN PERSON, WE HOPE THAT SHE IS WATCHING ON TV
AND WE WELCOME HER DAUGHTER CAROL, TEN, WHO IS HERE TO ON
HER BEHALF TO ACCEPT THIS HONOR AND TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> WELCOME CAROL. TEN.
>> I AM SO HONORED TO BE HERE ON BEHALF OF MY MOM WHO IS 104
AND SHE IS VERY FEISTY STILL. SHE STILL SCOLDS ME AND SHE IS
STILL A VERY HAPPY, VIBRANT PERSON AND SHE'S NOW IN A
NURSING HOME AND SHE ASKS EVERY CAREGIVER TO DANCE FOR HER
BECAUSE THAT'S THE ONLY WAY THEY CAN COMMUNICATE.
>> SHE CAN'T HEAR VERY WELL SO SHE'LL TELL THEM DANCE, YOU
KNOW, AND SHE'LL SHE'LL FORCE PEOPLE TO DANCE.
>> BUT I'M REALLY FORTUNATE TO HAVE A MOTHER LIKE HER.
WE WERE HERE WHEN I WAS 13 YEARS OLD IN 1973 ON OUR WAY
BACK TO THE PHILIPPINES BECAUSE SHE THOUGHT THE ONLY WAY I
COULD GROW TO BECOME A BETTER PERSON IS TO BE BROUGHT BACK TO
ASIA. >> BUT SHE WAS WRONG.
AND THEN I RETURNED HERE AFTER COLLEGE AND FELL IN LOVE WITH
SAN FRANCISCO IN 1982. BUT SHE TAGGED ALONG AND SHE
CAME TO VISIT ME AND SHE NEVER LEFT AND SHE FOUND THE JOB AS
SUCH VOLUNTEER AT SELF-HELP FOR THE ELDERLY WHO GRACIOUSLY TOOK
HER IN FOR OVER 30 YEARS UNDER THE WINGS OF ANNIE CHUNG
AND SHE HAS BEEN A DEDICATED, YOU KNOW, SERVER BECAUSE SHE
THOUGHT AS A SENIOR CITIZEN IT'S A PRIVILEGE TO GIVE BACK
ESPECIALLY TO THE UNITED STATES AND TO THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. I TOOK CARE OF MY MOM FOR THE
LAST THREE YEARS AND LEARNED MORE ABOUT HER AND SHE GAVE ME
THE COURAGE TO CONTINUE THIS CIVIC CITIZEN SHIP, YOU KNOW,
DUTY I'M ACTUALLY WORKING CURRENTLY FOR THE SCHOOL
DISTRICT FOUR TO SERVE OUR SPECIAL NEEDS STUDENTS THOUGH I
DON'T GET PAID AS WELL. >> YOU KNOW IF I HAD CHOSEN A
PRIVATE COMPANY TO WORK FOR BUT IT'S A CIVIC DUTY TO WORK FOR
THE CITY AND I'M PROUD TO BE PART OF IT PART OF THIS, YOU
KNOW, CITY AND ACTUALLY THE ONE WHO BROUGHT ME HERE WAS ONE OF
OUR DIRECTORS FROM ONE OF OUR SCHOOLS AND SOMEONE WHO I
CLOSELY WORKED WITH ALSO FOR THE SCHOOL DISTRICT AND IT'S
JUST SUCH AN HONOR TO LIVE IN THIS CITY AND HOPEFULLY I
WILL ALSO BE ABLE TO AFFORD TO LIVE HERE UNTIL I RETIRE
AND DIE HERE. >> BUT ANYWAY SO AGAIN THANK
YOU. IT'S AN HONOR TO RECEIVE THIS
ON BEHALF OF MY MOTHER IS BEAUTIFUL.
THANK YOU SO GRADUATIONS TO ONE AND FINALLY DISTRICT TEN
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT MOUNTAIN MAN IF I
COULD HAVE BILLY CORTESE COME UP TO THE PODIUM.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY WE ARE HONORING BILLY TETCHY AND THE
BELOVED NEIGHBORHOOD INSTITUTION IL PIRATA.
>> FOR GENERATIONS IL PIRATA HAS STOOD AS A GATHERING PLACE
FOR NEIGHBORS, ARTISTS AND FAMILIES A SPACE THAT
EMBODIES THE WARMTH, DIVERSITY AND CREATIVE SPIRIT THAT MAKES
SAN FRANCISCO TRULY SPECIAL. WILL BEGIN AS A FAMILY ENDEAVOR
HAS GROWN INTO A NEIGHBORHOOD LANDMARK PASSED DOWN AND CARED
FOR THROUGH GENERATIONS OF OWNERSHIP DEVOTED TO COMMUNITY
HOSPITALITY AND HEART. THIS IS NOT JUST A BUSINESS.
IT IS A LIVING LEGACY A PLACE WHERE PARENTS WANT BROUGHT
THEIR CHILDREN TO SHARE A MEAL OR A SONG.
AND WHERE THOSE SAME CHILDREN NOW RETURN AS ADULTS TO CREATE
MEMORIES OF THEIR OWN. THROUGH THE YEARS THE FAMILY
BEHIND IL PERATA HAS CONTINUED TO HONOR ITS ROOTS WHILE
WELCOMING NEW FACES. AND I KNOW BILLY'S SISTER
AND MOTHER ARE ALSO HERE AND SHARING THAT EVERYONE WHO
WALKS THROUGH THOSE DOORS FEELS AT HOME.
>> WHEN BILLY'S FAMILY TOOK OVER IL PIRATA BACK IN 1994,
PETROL HILL WAS A DIFFERENT PLACE BUT THROUGH EVERY WAVE OF
CHANGE THROUGH THE TECH BOOMS, THE BUILDING CRANES AND THE
RISING RENTS THEY KEPT IL PERATA GROUNDED.
THEY MADE SURE THERE WAS ALWAYS A PLACE FOR WORKING PEOPLE FOR
MUSICIANS, FOR DREAMERS, FOR ANYONE WHO NEEDED A GOOD MEAL,
GOOD MUSIC AND A FAMILIAR FACE BEHIND THE BAR.
FROM THE ENERGY OF ITS LEGENDARY SALSA NIGHTS TO ITS
ROLE AS A GATHERING PLACE FOR LOCALS AND VISITORS ALIKE, IL
PIRATA HAS ALWAYS BEEN MORE THAN A BAR.
IT HAS BEEN A CORNERSTONE OF PETRO HILL WHERE COMMUNITY
CULTURE AND CONNECTION THRIVE AND A CITY THAT CONTINUES TO
EVOLVE. IL PARADA REMINDS US OF WHAT
REMAINS CONSTANT THE POWER OF FAMILY, THE IMPORTANCE OF
NEIGHBORHOOD AND THE ENDURING VALUE OF PLACES THAT BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER. THEIR HOSPITALITY ISN'T ABOUT
BUSINESS IT'S ABOUT BELONGING. THEIR WARMTH, HUMOR AND QUIET
GENEROSITY HAS MADE IL PROVIDE A SECOND HOME FOR SO MANY.
TODAY WE GIVE OUR HEARTFELT THANKS TO BILLY COTATI AND HIS
ENTIRE FAMILY FOR THEIR VISION AND LOVE OF PEOPLE.
MAY IL PARADA CONTINUE TO BE A LIGHT IN OUR CITY AND A
REMINDER THAT COMMUNITY THRIVES WHEN WE MAKE ROOM FOR ONE
ANOTHER. THANK YOU BILLY FOR REMINDING
US THAT A NEIGHBORHOOD IS ONLY AS STRONG AS THE PEOPLE WHO
CARE ENOUGH TO KEEP IT TOGETHER.
AND THANK YOU IL PIRATA FOR BEING THAT GATHERING PLACE
AND FOR KEEPING PIETRO HILL'S HEART BEATING.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> VERY GRATEFUL.
VERY FORTUNATE TO BE HERE TO REPRESENT THE COURTESY FAMILY.
IT ALL STARTED WITH MY LATE FATHER BILL COURTESY WHO SHOWED
ME THE WAY, WHO IS HARD WORK AND DETERMINATION THAT I
FOLLOWED. WE JUST LAST MONTH WE TURNED 31
AND LIKE SHIMON JUST SAID, VERY FORTUNATE.
HIS SUPPORT DISTRICT AND SUPERVISOR THAT WE WENT
THROUGH EVERYTHING THAT WE DID THROUGH THE GOOD TIMES THE BAD
TIMES AND WE MADE IT THROUGH. >> AND IT'S A WHOLE LIFE CYCLE
OF FROM A BABY SHOWER TO MANY, MANY BIRTHDAY CELEBRATIONS TO
RETIREMENT PARTIES TO CELEBRATION OF LIFE PARTIES
MANY, MANY EVENTS AND GATHERING WITH LOCAL CITY PEOPLE FROM DP
TO PUBLIC WORKS. 911 JUST COUNTLESS HOLIDAY
PARTIES AND GATHERINGS. WE HAVE A BEAUTIFUL SPACE
AND WE LIKE TO DO COMMUNITY EVENTS LIKE FOOD DRIVES LIKE
CANNED FOOD BUCKETS FOR THAT WE DONATE TO FOOD BANKS.
AND ALSO WE DO LIKE TOY DRIVES WITH LIKE NINER 40 NINER WATCH
PARTIES. AND FOR LIKE CHRISTMAS FOR LIKE
THE KIDS TO LIKE CAN'T GET LIKE A LOT OF PRESENTS.
>> SO WE DO LIKE TOY DRIVES AND WE ALSO DO EXCUSE ME MANY,
MANY EVENTS. LIKE SHIMON MENTIONED THE SALSA
PARTY THAT WE'VE BEEN DOING FOR SINCE THE SPRING OF 2000 AND TO
LEAVEN LEGENDARY CUBAN SALSA PARTY THAT'S EVERY LAST FRIDAY
OF THE MONTH. AND THEN WE ALSO HAD A COMEDY
SHOW THAT RAN FOR MANY YEARS LIKE 16 YEARS AND MANY OF OUR
UP AND COMING COMICS IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT YOU SEE ON THE
BIG SCREEN NOW LIKE ALI WONG HASAN MINHAJ AND MANY, MANY
OTHERS. AND ALSO THE STAPLE OF OUR
BUSINESS IS OUR RESIDENTS AND BUSINESSES IN OUR DISTRICT
AND LIKE UPS HERE. AND USPS AND EXCUSE ME
AND WITHOUT THEIR LOYAL SUPPORT AND COMMUNITY GATHERING, YOU
KNOW I WOULDN'T BE HERE TODAY CONTINUING ON THIS LEGACY AT,
YOU KNOW, EL PIRATA AND BETRAYAL HILL JUST ACROSS
FROM THE ONE SITE OF SEAL STADIUM WHERE THE SAN FRANCISCO
GIANTS USED TO PLAY. AND RIGHT NEXT DOOR TO THE MAIN
UPS BUILDING IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND IT JUST AN AMAZING PLACE
AND AN EXPERIENCE AMAZING EXPERIENCE THAT MANY, MANY
FAMILIES HAVE ENJOYED. AND I'M VERY FORTUNATE TO HAVE
THAT EXPERIENCE IN MY LIFE. AND I JUST VERY HONORED AND I
JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU AGAIN TO SHERMAN WALTON AND THE
REST OF THE DISTRICT SUPERVISORS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> WE'LL PLAY THE VIDEO BELOW
AND PERCY HAS A QUICK VIDEO ON FOR BEING A GREAT RESTAURANT
AND BAR. IF YOU WANT TO BE AT THE BAR OR
GO OUT TO ONE OF OUR TWO PATIOS AND GET TOGETHER WITH FRIENDS
AND FAMILY. I HAVE KNOWN EL PRADO
RESTAURANT FOR A VERY, VERY LONG TIME.
IT'S A GREAT FAMILY PLACE DEFINITELY WHETHER IT BE FOR
DINNER, FOR DRINKS OR EVEN TO HOLD A PRIVATE PARTY OF YOUR
OWN. >> AND THE MOST POPULAR FOOD IS
PROBABLY OUR PIZZA. THE OPERATOR BURGER IS REALLY
BIG HERE. TWO OF OUR ENTREES HERE THAT
ARE MOST OFTEN ORDERED ARE STEAK AND SEAFOOD AND PEOPLE
REALLY ENJOY THAT. OUR SPECIALTY BEER IS CALLED IL
PIRATA AND IT'S A LOCAL CALIFORNIA MICROBREW.
>> ONE OF MY FAVORITE THINGS DEFINITELY WOULD BE THE STEAK
BRUSCHETTA, TOMATOES, GARLIC, FRESH BASIL ON TOASTED BREAD
AND OLIVE OIL. ABSOLUTELY DELICIOUS.
WHEN YOU COME HERE YOU FEEL PART OF THE FAMILY
YOU'LL COME UP. >> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, I'M
GOING TO ASK FOR A LITTLE HELP FROM OUR CLERK AND OUR CITY
ATTORNEY PERHAPS AND GETTING THROUGH THE NEXT LITTLE BIT OF
THIS MEETING WE HAVE A 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER TO HONOR FOR
WHICH ARE A COUPLE OF ITEMS 26 AND TEN EVEN.
BUT I BELIEVE WE NEED TO CONSIDER ITEM 37 BEFORE WE TAKE
UP 26 AND 27. AND SO AND WE WILL NEED TO TAKE
PUBLIC COMMENTS ON 37 BEFORE WE VOTE ON IT.
BUT THE PUBLIC COMMENTS THAT WE OPEN UP WILL NOT BE GENERAL
PUBLIC COMMENT. IT WILL BE PUBLIC COMMENTS ONLY
ON ITEM 37. SO MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL ITEM 37? >> ITEM 37 THIS IS A MOTION TO
SCHEDULE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO CONVENE A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TODAY NOVEMBER 4TH AT 3 P.M. TO HOLD
A PUBLIC HEARING TO CONSIDER THE ORDINANCE APPROPRIATING 9.1
MILLION FROM THE STATE AND FEDERAL REVENUE RISK
RESERVE TO THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY FOR CAL FRESH BENEFITS
OR BACKFILL IN FISCAL YEAR 2025 THROUGH 2026.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
SO IF WE APPROVE THIS MOTION WE WILL THEN HAVE A A SPECIAL
ORDER AT 3:00 THAT WILL INVOLVE A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE WITH A
PRESENTATION FROM TRENT MOORE FROM HCA AND THEN WE WILL VOTE
ON ITEM 27 ONE. BUT FIRST WE NEED TO TAKE
PUBLIC COMMENT ON ITEM 37. AGAIN, THAT'S JUST A SNAP ITEM.
MADAM CLERK COULD YOU PLEASE CALL FOR PUBLIC COMMENT ON ITEM
37? >> ALL RIGHT.
IF YOU ARE HERE IN THE CHAMBER TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT ON
ITEM 37 WHICH IS WHETHER OR NOT THE BOARD SHOULD CONVENE
IN CLOSED SESSION FOR ITEMS 26 WHICH IS THE PUBLIC HEARING
AND THEN THE ORDINANCE CONTAINED IN ITEM 27 AND NEVER
TO CORRECT MY MY CLERK BUT IT WOULD BE OPEN SESSION.
IT'LL BE A COMMITTEE IT WOULD BE A COMMITTEE THE WHOLE NOT A
CLOSED SESSION I THINK I SAID COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE.
>> IT'S A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT, I DON'T SEE ANY MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC COMING FORWARD. GREAT.
SO PUBLIC COMMENT ON ITEM 37 IS CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 37 ON
ITEM 37 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR
SCHROEDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES ALL RIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MOTION IS APPROVED MADAM CLERK COULD YOU TAKE US TO OUR 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDER ITEMS 26 AND 27. >> ITEM 26 IS THE BOARD
CONVENING A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE PURSUANT TO THE MOTION
THAT THEY JUST APPROVED ITEM 37 FOR A PUBLIC HEARING FOR THE
BOARD TO HOST A PUBLIC COMMENT ON ITEM 27 WHICH IS THE
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 9.1 MILLION FROM THE STATE
AND FEDERAL REVENUE RISK RESERVE TO THE HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY FOR CAL FRESH BENEFITS BACKFILL IN FISCAL YEAR 2025
THROUGH 2026 FOR CONSIDERATION AFTER THE PUBLIC HEARING.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. I AM VERY GLAD AND GRATEFUL TO
THE ADMINISTRATION THAT WE ARE ABLE TO CONSIDER THIS TODAY
AND ALSO OF COURSE TO GRANT START FOR THEIR MATCH.
AND WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO INVITE TRENT WARD, THE DIRECTOR
OF HCA TO PRESENT. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN
,MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TRENT RAW EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR, HUMAN
SERVICES AGENCY THE 9.1 MILLION WILL BE COUPLED AS PRESIDENT
GENTLEMAN SAID WITH CRYING START FOUNDATIONS GENEROUS
DONATION OF 9.1 MILLION WHICH IS IN THE FORM OF A CONTRACT
BETWEEN THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY AND THE SAN FRANCISCO
MARIN FOOD BANK FOR THE ENTIRE AMOUNT AND THEN THE FOOD BANK
IN TURN HAS A CONTRACT WITH A PRIVATE VENDOR CALLED GOOD CARD
AND GOOD CARD ALONG WITH THE FOOD BANK OPENS A JOINT BANK
ACCOUNT OF THAT AMOUNT FROM WHICH CAL FRESH RECIPIENTS CAN
DRAW THEIR FUNDS WHEN THEY ACTIVATE THEIR GIFT CARDS.
NOW LET ME WALK YOU THROUGH. SO THAT'S THAT'S HOW THE MONEY
WILL BE SPENT. LET ME WALK YOU THROUGH IT WITH
A LITTLE BIT OF CONTEXT AND SORT OF HOW THIS IS GOING
TO WORK. WELL, IT'S ALREADY WORKING
BECAUSE AS OF 11:00 THIS MORNING ONE HUNDRED AND 53
PEOPLE HAVE REDEEMED THEIR GIFT CARDS.
SO AS YOU KNOW BY NOW THE FEDERAL SHUT DOWN.
IT HAS FOR THE FIRST TIME EVER AFFECTED FEDERAL ENTITLEMENT
PROGRAMS OF WHICH HSA ADMINISTERS IT SPECIFICALLY
HALTING OF FEDERAL MONEY FOR THE CAL FRESH PROGRAM
IN CALIFORNIA AFFECTING OR ESSENTIALLY DELAYING OR NOT
ISSUING BENEFITS AT ALL IN NOVEMBER FOR 82,000
HOUSEHOLDS IN SAN FRANCISCO COMPRISING ABOUT 112,000 PEOPLE
AS I COMMUNICATE TO YOU LAST WEEK IN A MEMO OR A COUPLE OF
WEEKS AGO, THE AVERAGE HOUSEHOLD BENEFIT IS ABOUT
$275. AVERAGE INDIVIDUAL BENEFIT IS
ABOUT 178 OVER $20 MILLION IN CAL IN FEDERAL CAL FRESH
MONEY GOES TO RECIPIENTS EVERY MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IS
SPENT IN OUR LOCAL ECONOMY. >> AS YOU ALSO KNOW THE CALPERS
BENEFITS ARE NOT CASH THEY'RE NO LONGER FOOD STAMP COUPONS.
THEY'RE ISSUED ON AN ELECTRONIC BENEFIT TRANSFER CARD OR ABT
CARD THAT GETS LOADED EVERY MONTH DIRECTLY FROM THE FEDERAL
TREASURY, U.S. TREASURY THROUGH THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA TO THE
IBT VENDOR. I POINT THAT OUT BECAUSE SAN
FRANCISCO HAS NO ROLE IN THAT LOADING OF THE CARD MEANING
THAT WE CANNOT SHOULD WE FIND MONEY ON OUR OWN WE CAN'T
SIMPLY ADD TO THE EXISTING CARD WHICH LIMITED OUR OPTIONS
IN TERMS OF BACKFILLING BENEFITS.
>> SO WHAT WE DECIDED TO DO WHEN IT BECAME CLEAR THROUGH
THE MONTH OF OCTOBER THAT THE USDA WAS GOING TO RENEGE ON ITS
PROMISE OVER TIME TO CONTINUE TO PROVIDE SNAP BENEFITS
NATIONWIDE DUE TO THE SHUTDOWN ,WE PUT TOGETHER A WHOLE SORT
OF A SET OF SCENARIOS MY TEAM DID ALONG WITH THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE TO SORT OF WHAT IF WE HAD $2 MILLION?
WHAT COULD WE DO IF WE HAD 5 MILLION, IF WE HAD 10 MILLION
ETC. PIE IN THE SKY WAS IF WE GOT THE WHOLE 20 MILLION WHAT
WOULD WE DO? >> AND WE WE DECIDED AT THAT
POINT RATHER THAN FUNDING FOOD PANTRIES, THE FOOD BANK
AND OTHER COMMUNITY DISTRIBUTION POINTS WE REALLY
WANTED TO MAINTAIN THAT $20 MILLION THAT'S IN THE LOCAL
ECONOMY AND WE ALSO WANTED TO MAXIMIZE CHOICE FOR OUR OUR
CALPERS CLIENTS. MANY OF THEM WORK GOING TO A
FOOD PANTRY, YOU KNOW, IS IS WAITING IN LINE AND IT'S
DIFFICULT OBVIOUSLY HAVING A GROCERY CARD WHERE THEY CAN
CHOOSE WHAT THEY WANT IS PREFERABLE.
WE SET THAT PROPOSAL ON TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE KUNAL MODY
AND AND PEGGY MARIA HE SHOPPED IT TO TO SEVERAL FUNDERS I
THINK BUT CRANK START STEPPED UP WITH $9.1 MILLION CONTINGENT
ON THE CITY MATCHING THAT 9.1 THE STRUCTURE THAT WE HAD
PRESENTED TO THEM IS AS FOLLOWS BECAUSE THE WAY THE CAL FRESH
BENEFITS ARE CALCULATED PRETTY MUCH EVERY EACH OF THE 82,000
HOUSEHOLDS HAS A DIFFERENT BENEFIT AMOUNT BY A LITTLE BIT.
IT'S BASED ON HOUSEHOLD SIZE RENT BURDEN AND HOW MUCH THEY
PAY IN UTILITIES ETC. WE WEREN'T GOING TO ATTEMPT TO
MATCH DOLLAR FOR DOLLAR EACH EACH HOUSEHOLD THAT WOULD HAVE
BEEN ADMINISTRATIVELY IMPOSSIBLE.
>> SO INSTEAD WHAT WE DID IS WE TIERED THE BENEFIT AMOUNT SO A
HOUSEHOLD OF 1 OR 2 PEOPLE WOULD GET $200 IN A GROCERY
CARD, 3 TO 4 WOULD GET 350 AND THEN FIVE OR MORE WOULD GET
500. >> SO IN A SENSE SOME
HOUSEHOLDS MIGHT GET A LITTLE BIT MORE THAN WHAT THEY WERE
GETTING THROUGH CAL FRESH AND SOME MIGHT GET A LITTLE BIT
LESS QUICK START DID FUND THE 9.1 WE'RE HERE BEFORE FOR THE
SUPPLEMENTAL TO DRAW FROM THE RESERVE FOR THE OTHER 9.1 WE
GOT WORD THIS WAS A SPRINT LAST MONDAY AND FROM MONDAY OF LAST
WEEK TO FRIDAY THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY DRAFTED ALONG
WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE A CONTRACT A SOLE SOURCE
CONTRACT FOR $18.2 MILLION, A DATA SHARING AGREEMENT BECAUSE
THE COVERAGE DATA NEEDS TO BE PROTECTED.
SO THAT WAS WITH WITH THE VENDOR GOOD CARD.
>> I SIGNED THE CONTRACT AT 3 P.M. ON FRIDAY.
WE WORKED THROUGH THE WEEKEND WITH CITY REPRODUCTION AND THE
CITY MAIL TO AMOUNT TO TO PRINT AND MAIL OUT 82,000 INDIVIDUAL
LETTERS TO EACH HOUSEHOLD WHO ARE RECOVERIES RECIPIENTS
IN THEIR NATIVE LANGUAGE EACH OF THOSE LETTERS CONTAIN AN
ACTIVATION CODE SPECIFIC TO THAT HOUSEHOLD WITH THAT ALLOWS
THEM TO ACTIVATE THEIR VIRTUAL GIFT CARD USING THAT CODE ALONG
WITH SOME PERSONAL IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION WHICH I'M NOT GOING
TO SPECIFY HERE JUST SORT OF FRAUD PROTECTION BUT THEY HAVE
TO VERIFY THAT IT'S THE PERSON ON THE LETTER AND THAT THEY ARE
BENEFITS OF OR RECIPIENTS OF CAL FRESH RECIPIENTS ALSO HAVE
AN OPTION FOR A PHYSICAL CARD THEY CAN CONTACT THE CALL
CENTER FOR GIFT CARD THEY COULD GET ISSUED A PHYSICAL CARD
AND IT WOULD BE MAILED WITHIN 5 TO 7 BUSINESS DAYS OF 100
AND 50 OR SO WHO HAVE ACTIVATED SO FAR 52% OF THEM CHOSE THE
VIRTUAL ROUTE. THE REMAINDER OF CHOSE THE
PHYSICAL CARD. THE VIRTUAL ONE SIMPLY GOES ON
YOUR YOUR APPLE PAY OR YOUR GOOGLE WALLET OR OR WHATEVER WE
HAVE PROVIDED TOOLKITS TO CBOS TO HELP CLIENTS NAVIGATE THAT
ACTIVATION SHOULD THEY HAVE QUESTIONS?
SENIOR CENTERS FAMILY RESOURCE CENTERS ARE HOMELESS SHELTERS
OR NAVIGATION CENTERS. IN ADDITION, AS I SAID, GOOD
CARD HAS A18 HUNDRED NUMBER FOR A CALL CENTER BECAUSE THERE
MIGHT BE CAPACITY ISSUES WE HAVE LINKED TO THEIR CALL
CENTER SO OVERFLOW CALLS NOW FLOW INTO THE HUMAN SERVICES
AGENCY'S BENEFIT CENTER SERVICE CENTER TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE.
>> I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT BOTH GOOD CARD
AND THE FOOD BANK ARE DOING THIS WORK PRO BONO.
GOOD CARD WILL CHARGE $5 FOR EACH PHYSICAL CARD THAT THEY
HAVE TO MAIL AND THAT'S JUST COVERING THEIR COSTS.
>> IF ALL 82,000 HOUSEHOLDS REQUESTED A PHYSICAL CARD IT
WOULD COST US $410,000 WHICH IN TERMS OF A PERCENTAGE OF THE
TOTAL IS VERY SMALL, WE KNOW THAT NOT EVERYONE WILL NEED
THAT THAT PHYSICAL CARD. >> HOW WILL CLIENTS FIND OUT?
A LOT OF CLIENTS MIGHT NOT EVEN KNOW THAT THEIR CARD WILL BE
LOADED BECAUSE OF THE FEDERAL SHUTDOWN.
SO WE SENT AS I SAID, 82,000 LETTERS THIS MORNING OVER
90,000 TEXT MESSAGES WENT OUT TO 112,000 CONFERENCE
RECIPIENTS INFORMING THEM THAT THEIR BENEFITS WILL BE DELAYED
AND THAT THEY SHOULD EXPECT A LETTER REGARDING THE GROCERY
CARD IN THE MAIL. >> THE GROCERY CARD CAN ONLY BE
USED AT POINT OF SALE MACHINES IN GROCERY STORES, MARKETS FOR
FOOD OR FOR PREPARED MEALS. >> WARM MEALS THAT ARE PREPARED
CAN'T BE USED IN RESTAURANTS, CAN'T BE USED FOR ALCOHOL,
CAN'T BE USED FOR TOBACCO, ALSO CANNOT BE CONVERTED TO CASH.
YOU CAN'T GET MONEY OUT OF AN ATM.
YOU CAN'T USE IT TO TRANSFER MONEY INTO INTO A CHECKING
ACCOUNT. >> LET'S SEE WHAT ELSE.
OH REALLY IMPORTANT PIECE THAT THAT WE SORT OF STRUGGLE
THROUGH BUT WE THINK WE HAVE A AS ELEGANT A SOLUTION AS
POSSIBLE FOR OUR CALPERS CLIENTS WHO DON'T HAVE A FIXED
ADDRESS. WE HAVE ABOUT 8000 RECIPIENTS
WHO USE WHAT'S CALLED GENERAL DELIVERY WHICH IS THE POST
OFFICE ON HIGH STREET TO GET THEIR CORRESPONDENCE FROM US.
ABOUT 85% OF THEM ARE PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS.
WHAT WE ARE DOING FOR THEM AGAIN THEY CAN ACTIVATE THE
CARDS VIRTUALLY WITHOUT EVEN A LETTER PROVIDED THAT THEY HAVE
THEIR THEIR IB CARD NUMBER AND THEIR IDENTIFIABLE
INFORMATION TO PROVE IT TO THEM.
>> BUT WE ARE ALSO GOING TO OPEN UP OUR OFFICES, OUR
DISTRIBUTION OFFICES AT 1235 MISSION STREET MISSION BETWEEN
EIGHTH AND NINTH STARTING THURSDAY TO GIVE ACTIVATE
AND PROVIDE PHYSICAL CARDS TO PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS OR OTHERS WHO USE THE GENERAL DELIVERY ADDRESS.
>> WE ARE PARTNERING WITH CODE TENDERLOIN WHOSE OFFICES ARE
LITERALLY RIGHT NEXT DOOR THAT WE SHARE A WALL AND THEY'RE
OPENING AN ADDITIONAL SIX DESKS KIOSKS IF YOU WILL, TO HELP
INDIVIDUALS. >> WE'RE UNDER NO ILLUSIONS
THIS IS 8000 PEOPLE. THERE ARE GOING TO BE LINES
DOWN MISSION STREET. WE'RE GOING TO DO EVERYTHING WE
CAN TO MITIGATE THAT IN ADDITION TO THE CODE
TENDERLOIN WINDOWS WE HAVE FOUR WINDOWS AT EIGHT TO SAY WE WILL
LIKELY OPEN UP ADDITIONAL WINDOWS IN OUR LOBBY.
WE WILL ALSO HAVE VOLUNTEERS FROM HCA AND POTENTIALLY CBOS
WORKING THE LINES WITH TABLETS ACTIVATING FOR THOSE
INDIVIDUALS WAITING IN LINE WHO HAVE WHO HAVE SMARTPHONES
AND CAN USE A DIGITAL CARD WE CAN ACTIVATE THEM IN LINE SO
THEY DON'T HAVE TO WAIT FOR A PHYSICAL CARD.
AGAIN THAT BEGINS ON ON THURSDAY.
THAT'S SORT OF IT FOR THE YOU KNOW, THE OVERVIEW I DO HAVE TO
SAY THAT THIS IS A HERCULEAN EFFORT ON NOT JUST BY HSA STAFF
OR BY THE CITY MAYOR'S OFFICE GREAT PARTNERSHIP WITH KUNAL
MODI AND PEGGY MORIARITY AND ALSO ADAM SAN FRANCISCO
MARIN FOOD BANK AND THEN EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR TANNIS
CROSBY. I CALLED HER TWO WEEKS AGO
AND I SAID HEY, WHAT CAN YOU GUYS DO IF WE GIVE YOU $10
MILLION, $15 MILLION COULD YOU EXPAND YOUR PANTRIES?
SHE SAID SURE. WHEN WE DECIDED TO GO A
DIFFERENT DIRECTION WITH THE CARDS CALLED TANNIS AND SHE
SAID NO PROBLEM WILL BE THE INTERMEDIARY AND YOU KNOW, THEY
PIVOTED AND YOU KNOW ON A DIME CITY ATTORNEY TEAM GETTING A
CONTRACT FROM FROM A BLANK PAGE TO CERTIFICATION AND SIGNATURE
AND FIVE DAYS IS UNPRECEDENTED TREASURER'S OFFICE THEY LINKED
UP WITH THE VENDOR GOOD CARD AND ARE HELPING WITH THE
POLICIES AND PROCEDURES FOR SORT OF THE FRAUD SAFEGUARDS
THAT WE'RE PUTTING IN PLACE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE SO
HSA HAS OUR OWN PRINTING AND MAILING CAPACITY.
WE MAILED OUT NOTICES TO OUR 250,000 CLIENTS ON A REGULAR
BASIS. OF COURSE LAST WEEK ON
WEDNESDAY TWO OF OUR PRINTERS COPIERS WERE DOWN.
>> I CALLED CARMEN CHU AND SHE IMMEDIATELY STEPPED UP NOT ONLY
TO SAY THAT THEY WILL HELP BUT WHEN I SAID THAT WE NEEDED THEM
TO WORK THROUGH THE WEEKEND AND THAT HSA WOULD PAY FOR
THEIR OVERTIME, SHE GOT BACK TO ME WITHIN A HALF HOUR AND SAID
HER STAFF WERE MORE THAN HAPPY TO WORK THROUGH THE WEEK
THROUGH THE HALLOWEEN WEEKEND TO GET THOSE LETTERS OUT
AND THEY WENT OUT MONDAY AROUND 6 P.M. H.S. DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELESSNESS IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING USE THROUGH THEIR
COMMUNITY NETWORKS. >> ALL OF THEIR CBO PARTNERS
DROP IN CENTER SHELTERS TO GET THE WORD OUT TO PEOPLE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS AND LITERALLY EVERY DIVISION AT
HSA WORKED TIRELESSLY FROM OUR I.T. CONTRACTS, COMMUNICATIONS
PLANNING AND POLICY LED THE EFFORT.
IT WAS REALLY AN AMAZING UNDERTAKING AND AND JUST HAVE
TO SAY I'M VERY PROUD OF NOT ONLY MY STAFF BUT THE WAY THE
CITY STEPPED UP TO MEET THE FOOD NEEDS OF 82,000 PEOPLE WHO
OTHERWISE WOULD HAVE BEEN FORGOTTEN BY THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT. SO I'LL CONCLUDE WITH THAT
AND OBVIOUSLY HAPPY TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS.
>> THANK YOU. DIRECTOR ROGER GREAT WORK
EVERYONE. SUPERVISOR SLAUGHTER THANK YOU.
>> PRESIDENT THANK YOU FOR STEPPING UP AND THANK YOU FOR
SHARING THAT BACKGROUND. IT DOES SOUND LIKE A HERCULEAN
EFFORT AND IT'S SOMETHING WE SHOULD ALL BE PROUD OF.
JUST BRIEFLY MAYBE A QUESTION AND A SUGGESTION THE IF IF YOU
KNOW WE DON'T KNOW HOW MANY SIGNUPS THERE WILL BE YOU KNOW,
153 IS A GOOD START BUT FOR MONEY THAT IS NOT UTILIZED.
SO WHERE DOES THAT GO? AND THEN YOU KNOW, JUST A
UNSOLICITED SUGGESTION BUT ON THE ON THE STACK OF WEBSITE
THAT YOU KNOW, TOP BANNER TODAY IS OF COURSE ABOUT THE ELECTION
AS IT SHOULD BE. BUT MAYBE YOU COULD GET THAT
SPOT TOMORROW FOR THE NEXT WEEK.
I'M SURE YOU ALREADY WORKING ON THAT BUT I JUST I WANT I WANT
THIS TO BE EVERYWHERE AND YOU KNOW, WE SHOULD DO THAT AS A
BOARD TO GET THIS OUT TO OUR NETWORKS AND CONSTITUENTS AS
WELL. BUT BUT MY FIRST QUESTION ON
WHERE ON USE MONEY MIGHT MIGHT GO WHAT HAPPENS?
GREAT QUESTION. >> SUPERVISOR RECIPIENTS OF CAL
FRESH AND OF THE CARDS HAVE UNTIL DECEMBER 31ST OF THIS
YEAR TO ACTIVATE THE CARDS AND THEN THEY HAVE UNTIL THE
END OF MARCH OF 26 TO SPEND ALL THE FUNDS THAT ARE UNSPENT AS
OF APRIL 1ST 26 WELL ON A 5050 BASIS RETURN TO THE GENERAL
FUND AND TO CRANK START THANK YOU.
>> AND THEN IN TERMS OF THE MARKETING YOUR WHAT TOP BANNER
ON ON THE HSA WEBSITE IS CERTAINLY THE CAL FRESH
REPLACEMENT I SUGGESTED ABOUT THE CITY WIDE WEBSITE.
>> THE THE CBO TOOLKIT IS ALSO HIGHLIGHTED IT IS IT IS QUITE
EXTENSIVE AND EVERYTHING FROM 11 BY 17 FLIERS TO STEP BY STEP
INSTRUCTIONS HOW EMPLOYEES OF COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATIONS
AND OTHERS CAN HELP PEOPLE ACTIVATE THEIR CARDS OR ORDER
PHYSICAL CARDS SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PRESIDENT I1I JUST
WANT TO APPRECIATE AND SAY THANK YOU TO DIRECTOR MOHLER
AND EVERYONE AND THAT IT'S INVOLVED AND IN YOUR TEAM TO
MAKING THIS IN A SHORT TURNAROUND INTO A REALITY.
I JUST WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT AND THANK YOU FOR THE HOT WORK
AND I AM INCREDIBLY PROUD OF OUR CITY STEPPING OUT FOR FOUR
FOR ALL THE RESIDENTS AT THIS TIME.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT, LET'S OPEN THIS. I HAD A TROUBLE COMMENT.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, EVERYONE. I JUST WANT TO SAY GREAT JOB.
I'M NOT MAKING THIS POLITICAL AND DOING THE RIGHT THING FOR
THE CITIZENS OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> SO THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER BOARD OF SUPERVISOR AND MAYOR
OFFICE OF SAN FRANCISCO. THE TITLE OF MY SPEECH TODAY IS
ARE YOU A WOLF OR YOUR SHEEP? >> I THINK THIS MIGHT BE
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT YOU ARE PROVIDING AND RIGHT NOW WE ARE
ONLY TAKING PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE
APPROPRIATION. STATE AND FEDERAL REVENUE RISK
RESERVE HUMAN SERVICE AGENCY CAL FRESH SNAP BENEFITS
BACKFILL IN THE AMOUNT OF $9,100,000 W R DUFFY DISTRICT
FIVE I JUST WANT TO COMPLIMENT ALSO DIRECTOR OR SURPRISINGLY
LONG CAREER IN A DIFFICULT POSITION.
ARE THERE OTHER SPEAKERS TO ADDRESS THIS ISSUE?
>> ALL RIGHT MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS CLOSED SEEING OH SUPERVISOR WALDEN THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT. GENTLEMEN, I JUST WANTED TO
LEND MY VOICE TO THE CHORUS AND SAY THANK YOU TO THE
DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN SERVICES. >> I DEFINITELY REACHED OUT TO
DIRECTOR OR IMMEDIATELY AND HE ALREADY HAD HAD CONVERSATIONS
WITH PHILANTHROPY AND ALREADY WAS SET TO MOVE FORWARD WITH
THE PLAN TO ADDRESS THE GAPS. SO I JUST WANT TO LET YOU KNOW
WE APPRECIATE YOU AND THANKS FOR COMING UP WITH SOMETHING SO
QUICKLY. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALDEN AND I DO HAVE TO THANK ALL 11 MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD FOR SO QUICKLY EMBRACING THE THE SUGGESTION AND THE
ACTION OF GETTING FUNDS OFF RESERVE FOR THIS THIS CAUSE
IT'S IT'S NICE TO SEE THE CITY FAMILY COMING TOGETHER ALL AS
ONE ON THIS THANK YOU DIRECTOR AND THANKS TO ALL OF YOUR
PARTNERS CITY GOVERNMENT AS WELL OUR TREASURER TAX
COLLECTOR AND AS I SAID IT MAKES ME VERY PROUD TO BE A SAN
FRANCISCAN THAT WE'RE ABLE TO DO THIS AND THAT WE ARE DOING
THIS AND FORTUNATE THAT WE HAVE RESERVES.
THANK YOU JERRY CHAN AND AND MAYOR LARRY AND THAT WE HAVE
PRIVATE PHILANTHROPY PHILANTHROPY WITH THE POCKETS
TO TO BE ABLE TO DO THIS AND OF COURSE MOST PLACES IN THIS
COUNTRY ARE NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO DO THAT AND THAT IS
HORRIFYING. >> ALL RIGHT.
SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER, THIS MATTER HAS BEEN
HEARD AND IS NOW FILED AND WE WILL NOW CONSIDER ITEM 27
AND MADAM CLERK, DO I NEED A MOTION ON THIS OR DO I DO WE
JUST NO, MR. PRESIDENT JUST CALLED IT MR. PRESIDENT.
>> MAYBE IT WILL BE YES, YES, YES, YES, YES, I DO.
ALL RIGHT. SO YOU'RE GOING TO BE ASKING
FOR IT TO BE APPROVED ON FIRST READING BUT ALSO CONTINUE TO.
OH, THAT'S RIGHT. A SPECIAL BOARD MEETING OF
NOVEMBER 10TH I BELIEVE IT 10 A.M..
>> THANK YOU SO OH BECAUSE WE YES COLLEAGUES WE'RE DOING A WE
ARE DOING A SPECIAL MEETING ON NOVEMBER 10TH AT LEAST WE WILL
IF YOU ALL AGREE. SO MAY I HAVE A MOTION TO PASS
THIS ORDINANCE ON FIRST READING AND SEND IT TO THE NOVEMBER
10TH SPECIAL MEETING MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY WALTON.
>> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO
APPROVE THIS ORDINANCE ON FIRST READING AND FORWARD TO THE
BOARD MEETING THE SPECIAL BOARD MEETING OF NOVEMBER 10TH AT 10
A.M.. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MIKE WOULD LIKE MORE
EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SORTER SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
AND WILL BE SENT TO THE NOVEMBER 10TH SPECIAL BOARD
MEETING. THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR BEING
WILLING TO DO THAT AND NOW MADAM CLERK I THINK WE GO BACK
TO ROLL CALL. >> YES WE LEFT OFF AND IT IS
SUPERVISOR FIELDER WHO'S NEXT UP.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I WANT TO PRESENT
AN IN MEMORIAM IN HONOR OF KIT KAT THE BELOVED BODEGA CAT WHO
WAS ADOPTED BY MY SAID IN THE OWNER AND OPERATOR OF RANDY'S
MARKET ON 16TH STREET IN THE MISSION KIT KAT WAS STRUCK
AND KILLED BY A WAYMO ROBOTAXI LAST MONDAY IN A TRAGIC
INCIDENT. IT'S ACTUALLY KNOWN AS MAYOR OF
16TH STREET. >> KIT KAT ARRIVED AT THE
MARKET SIX YEARS AGO AND SINCE THEN BECAME A NEIGHBORHOOD
FIXTURE AND A TRUE ICON OF 16TH STREET A FAMILIAR FELINE FACE
EVERY PERSON THAT WALKS BY OR INTO THE MARKET, KIT KAT WOULD
CALMLY GREET CINEPHILES AS THEY LEFT THE ROXY OR PATRONS FROM
DARVA AND DELIRIUM ALWAYS READY FOR LOVING PETS FROM REGULARS
AND NEW VISITORS ALIKE ONE OF THE KIND CAT IT WOULD NOT BE AN
OVERSTATEMENT TO SAY THAT ANYONE WHO EVER SPENT ANY TIME
ON THE ICONIC 16TH STREET CORRIDOR IN THE MISSION KNEW OF
KIT KAT. HE REPRESENTED EVERY THING THAT
MAKES THE MISSION DISTRICT SPECIAL.
HE WAS FRIENDLY, BRAVE AND DEEPLY ROOTED IN HIS
COMMUNITY. I CERTAINLY APPRECIATED SEEING
HIM WHENEVER I WOULD GO TO THE ROXY DAUBER ANY OF THE
WONDERFUL RESTAURANTS AND BARS ON THAT STREET.
KIT KAT AND OUR PETS ARE LIVING CREATURES WITH INHERENT VALUE
THAT DESERVE DIGNITY AND OUR RESPECT.
IF THE MEASURE OF ANY SOCIETY IS IN THE WAY IT TREATS THOSE
WHO ARE THE WEAKEST THEN KIT KAT DEATH DESERVES OUR SORROW.
OUR REVERENCE AND OUR REGRET AND THIS INCIDENT THAT RESULTED
IN KIT COUNT'S TRAGIC DEATH DESERVES JUST AS MUCH SCRUTINY
AND ATTENTION AS A DEATH OF ANY OTHER.
AND A FRIEND THAT POPPED UP OUTSIDE OF RANDY'S MARKET
IN THE DAYS AFTER KIT KATS PASSING WITH HUNDREDS OF
OFFERINGS FROM THE MANY LIVES HE HAS TOUCHED THE OUTPOURING
OF SUPPORT, THE COUNTLESS STORIES AND MANY, MANY MEMORIES
WITH KIT KAT ARE A TESTAMENT TO JUST HOW VITAL HIS ROLE ON 16TH
STREET WAS AND THE JOY THAT HE BROUGHT TO PEOPLE'S LIVES.
>> THE MISSION WILL NOT BE THE SAME WITHOUT OUR KIT KAT
HOWEVER HIS MEMORY AND LEGACY LIVE ON IN OUR HEARTS REST
IN PEACE. AND ON THAT NOTE I AM ALSO
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TODAY CALLING ON THE CALIFORNIA
LEGISLATURE AND THE GOVERNOR TO GIVE LOCAL COMMUNITIES THE
POWER TO DECIDE FOR THEMSELVES WHETHER AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES
SHOULD BE ALLOWED TO OPERATE ON THE ROADS.
STATE LAW FIRST AUTHORIZED AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES ON PUBLIC
ROADS IN 2012 AND LAST YEAR THE CALIFORNIA LEGISLATURE
CONSIDERED SB 915 WHICH WOULD HAVE ALLOWED MUNICIPAL
GOVERNMENTS SOME CONTROL OVER THEIR DEPLOYMENT.
>> THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN MARCH OF 2024 UNANIMOUSLY
PASSED A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING THAT BILL.
UNFORTUNATELY THAT BILL DID NOT PASS IN PART DUE TO CONCERNS
ABOUT MAINTAINING INTERCITY CONSISTENCY.
>> SINCE THEN THE PROLIFERATION OF AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES IN SAN
FRANCISCO HAS CONTINUED TO RAISE SIGNIFICANT PRIVACY
WORKFORCE ENVIRONMENTAL TRAFFIC AND PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION
CONCERNS. THIS RESOLUTION PROPOSES A PATH
FORWARD RATHER THAN LEAVING CITIES POWERLESS.
>> IT CALLS ON THE STATE LEGISLATURE AND THE GOVERNOR TO
GRANT LOCAL COMMUNITIES AT THE COUNTY LEVEL THE RIGHT TO
DECIDE WHETHER AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES SHOULD OPERATE WITHIN
THEIR JURISDICTIONS. BY DOING SO WE CAN PROMOTE MORE
LOCAL DEMOCRACY, ENSURE REGIONAL COORDINATION AND GIVE
COMMUNITIES A REAL VOICE IN SHAPING THE FUTURE OF OUR
TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS
CHAN CHEN AND WALTON FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP.
LET'S SEND A CLEAR MESSAGE TO SACRAMENTO.
LOCAL COMMUNITIES DESERVE A SAY IN WHETHER AUTONOMOUS VEHICLES
OPERATE ON OUR STREETS. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES LAST WEEK I SPOKE
ABOUT HOW THE NEWS OF A POTENTIAL NATIONAL GUARD SURGE
LEFT MANY OF OUR RESIDENTS FEELING ANXIOUS AND UNCERTAIN
ABOUT WHAT COMES NEXT IN OUR CITY.
>> AS REPRESENTATIVES FOR OUR DISTRICTS IT IS OUR JOB TO DO
EVERYTHING IN OUR POWER TO KEEP OUR RESIDENTS SAFE AND AT EASE.
IN FACT, SAN FRANCISCO'S LONG PRIDED ITSELF ON BEING A
SANCTUARY CITY A PLACE WHERE EVERYONE REGARDLESS OF
BACKGROUND OR IMMIGRATION STATUS KNOWS THEY BELONG
AND TRUSTS THAT THEY ARE WELCOME.
>> IN THE PAST FEW WEEKS WE'VE HEARD QUESTIONS FROM COMMUNITY
ABOUT THE NATIONAL GUARD. SO TODAY I'D LIKE TO CLARIFY A
FEW POINTS. >> I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
RECOGNIZING THAT OUR SANCTUARY CITY ORDINANCE STILL STANDS
STRONG AND PROHIBITS THE USE OF CITY RESOURCES TO ASSIST ANY
FEDERALLY DEPLOYED NATIONAL GUARD PERSONNEL OR OTHER
FEDERAL AGENTS ENGAGED IN CIVIL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
>> IT IS A REAFFIRMATION OF THE CITY'S ENDURING COMMITMENT TO
SUPPORT IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES BECAUSE SANCTUARY POLICIES
EMBODY OUR VALUES OF INCLUSION, DIGNITY AND THE RIGHTS OF ALL
PEOPLE TO LIVE FREE FROM DISCRIMINATION, HARASSMENT OR
INTIMIDATION REGARDLESS OF IMMIGRATION STATUS.
>> THIS POLICY HAS SET THE MODEL FOR THE REST OF THE
NATION FOR DECADES AND I WANT TO REITERATE THAT THESE
SANCTUARY PROTECTIONS APPLY EQUALLY TO ANY FEDERAL ENTITY
CONDUCTING CIVIL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT WHETHER IT'S ICE
FEDERALIZED NATIONAL GUARD TROOPS OR OTHER AGENCIES LIKE
THE DEA AND ATF THAT COULD BE TAPPED FOR CIVIL IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT. >> OUR CITY RESOURCES WILL NOT
BE USED TO ASSIST IN CIVIL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
>> I'VE SAID THIS BEFORE. WHAT OUR RESIDENTS WANT MOST IS
TO FEEL SAFE, TO FEEL PROTECTED AND TO KNOW THAT THE CITY HAS
THEIR BACK. >> SO TO OUR RESIDENTS WHO ARE
WATCHING, WE STAND WITH OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES.
WE STAND WITH RESIDENTS AGAINST FEAR AND DISCRIMINATION AND WE
WILL CONTINUE TO KEEP OUR RESIDENTS SAFE NO MATTER WHAT
COMES OUR WAY. I'D LIKE TO THANK S.F. RISING
AND IRAQ FOR SUPPORTING THIS RESOLUTION.
AND THANKS TO OUR DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI AND MY
CHIEF OF STAFF JESSICA GUTIERREZ GARCIA AND MOST
IMPORTANTLY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM LOGAN FOR WORKING
IN OUR OFFICE ON THIS LEGISLATION.
>> I LIKE TO ALSO THANK SUPERVISOR CHEN WALTON, SADR
CHAN AND FIELDER FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AS WELL
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. I HAVE A COUPLE OF IN MEMORIAM
TODAY. FIRST I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF GARY MCLEAN KNOWN
TO MANY BY DRAG NAME MALINA WHO DIED ON OCTOBER 5TH AT THE AGE
OF 85. GARY MCLAIN WAS BORN ON
NOVEMBER 14TH, 1939 IN CALIFORNIA'S CENTRAL VALLEY
. HE DIVORCED, DIVORCED HIS WIFE
AND CAME OUT AS A GAY MAN IN 1973 AFTER WHICH HE WOULD
BECOME KNOWN FOR HIS WORK WITH THE IMPERIAL COURT, A
NATIONWIDE PHILANTHROPIC LGBTQ PLUS NONPROFIT.
PRIOR TO COMING TO SAN FRANCISCO, GARY REIGNED AS
MARLENA EMPRESS THREE OF THE IMPERIAL AISLE EMPIRE OF
MODESTO. IN 1990 HE WAS CROWNED ABSOLUTE
EMPRESS 25 MARLENA THE MAGNIFICENT OF THE IMPERIAL
COURT OF SAN FRANCISCO. AND IN FEBRUARY HE COMPLETED
HIS 35TH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION.
EMPRESS MARLENA WAS KNOWN FOR HER WARMTH, MENTORSHIP
AND FLAIR. SHE WAS SO INFLUENTIAL THAT SHE
WAS CROWNED THE FIRST QUEEN MOTHER, ONE OF CALIFORNIA BY
NICOLE MARIE RAMIREZ. QUEEN MOTHER ONE OF THE
AMERICA'S. IN 1989, FOLLOWING THE LOMA
PRIETA EARTHQUAKE, GARY OPENED MARLENA, A SELF-DESCRIBED
OASIS IN HIS VALLEY A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HAD
HISTORICALLY LACKED PUBLIC SPACES.
GARY'S NAME WAS ON THE LIST BUT IT WAS TRULY MARLENA WHO RAN
THE BAR THAT BECAME A CORNERSTONE OF THE HAYS VALLEY
COMMUNITY. MARLENA WAS KNOWN FOR ITS
VIBRANT DRAG SHOWS COMMUNITY FUNDRAISERS AND A LEGENDARY
CHRISTMAS SANTA DISPLAYS. IT BECAME A REFUGE FROM THE
DESPAIR OF THE AIDS EPIDEMIC. EVEN AFTER SELLING THE BAR
IN 2012, MARLENA REMAINED A PILLAR OF THE COMMUNITY.
FRIENDS AND FELLOW MONARCHS DESCRIBED HER AS SOMEONE WHO
ACCEPTED EVERY EVERYBODY AND BECAME AN EXTENDED VERSION
OF THEIR FAMILY. MARLENA IS SURVIVED BY HER
DAUGHTER PAMELA HARRINGTON. HER SON GARY MCLEAN, HER EIGHT
GRANDCHILDREN 13 GREAT GRANDCHILDREN AND A LARGE
EXTENDED FAMILY OF FRIENDS FROM THE IMPERIAL COURT AND AN
IMPERIAL STATE FUNERAL WILL BE HELD ON SATURDAY NOVEMBER
EIGHTH AT NOON AT ST MARK'S LUTHERAN CHURCH FOLLOWED BY A
CELEBRATION OF LIFE OUTSIDE HER FORMER BAR AT 2 P.M. FEATURING
THE RETURN OF THE HAYES STREET FOLLIES AND PERFORMANCES BY THE
SAN FRANCISCO IMPERIAL MONARCHS.
WE SEND OUR DEEP CONDOLENCES TO MARLENA, THE FAMILY, FRIENDS
AND THE ENTIRE IMPERIAL IMPERIAL COURT COMMUNITY.
REST IN PEACE AND POWER EMPRESS MARLENA THE MAGNIFICENT.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING AND YOUR CROWN FOREVER SHINE
FOR SAN FRANCISCO. SECONDLY, I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF DEANNA GWEN
CRAWFORD MOONEY WHO DIED ON OCTOBER 2ND, 2025 AT THE AGE OF
84. DEANNA WAS BORN OCTOBER 5TH,
1940 AND WOODWARD, OKLAHOMA, THE ELDEST CHILD OF GWEN
SOUTHER AND IVAN CRAWFORD. SHE GREW UP IN ENID, OKLAHOMA
WHERE SHE ATTENDED MCKINLEY ELEMENTARY.
EMERSON JUNIOR HIGH AND ENID HIGH SCHOOL BEFORE EARNING A
NURSING DEGREE FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA IN 1961.
DEANNA MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO AND BEGAN A CAREER AT SAN
FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL WHERE SHE WOULD WORK FOR NEARLY
FOUR DECADES. THERE SHE LED THE COUNTRY'S
FIRST NURSE SICKOUT IN 1966 TO DEMAND FAIR PAY AND BETTER
WORKING CONDITIONS AND LATER HELPED SECURE LIFETIME HEALTH
CARE FOR CITY NURSES AND THEIR FAMILIES.
SHE ALSO HELPED OVERSEE THE HOSPITAL'S RELOCATION IN THE
1970S AND WORKED ON NATIONAL TASK FORCES THAT DEVELOPED THE
FIRST AIDS TREATMENT PROTOCOLS WITH THE CDC, FDA AND IHS
IN THE 1980S. OUTSIDE HER NURSING CAREER
AND ADVOCACY, DIANA WORKED AS A SET DECORATOR FOR WARNER
BROTHERS CONTRIBUTING TO ICONIC SAN FRANCISCO FILMS INCLUDING
BULLITT AND THE DIRTY HARRY SERIES.
IN 1964 SHE WAS INTRODUCED TO HER HUSBAND SEAN MOONEY THROUGH
ABC NIGHTLY NEWS ANCHOR PETER JENNINGS.
TOGETHER THEY SUPPORTED SHAWN'S VENTURES IN HOSPITALITY,
INCLUDING MONROE'S RESTAURANT AND MOONEY'S IRISH PUB.
IN 1971 THEY ATTEMPTED TO HAVE A SECRET WEDDING ON A TUESDAY
THAT BECAME A CITYWIDE EVENT AFTER IT WAS ANNOUNCED OVER
HOSPITAL LOUDSPEAKERS MENTIONED BY RADIO HOST JIM DUNBAR
AND CELEBRATED IN HERB CAEN'S COLUMN.
DIANA AND SHAWN SHARED A LOVE OF LAUGHTER, TRAVEL
AND ENTERTAINING. THEY LIVED ON TELEGRAPH HILL
AND LATER IN NOMI VALLEY AND SPENT SUMMERS AT THEIR
SIERRA RETREAT. KNOWN AS THE CABIN WHERE
FRIENDS AND FAMILY GATHERED FOR BARBECUES, CARD GAMES AND DECK
LIVING AFTER SHAWN'S DEATH IN 1990, DIANA CONTINUED TO
LIVE LIFE TO ITS FULLEST TRAVELING THE WORLD AND JOINING
SAN FRANCISCO'S CAFÉ SCENE AND EARNING THE NICKNAME THE
SALOON STAR FROM THE MARINA TIMES FOR HER CHARM, HUMOR
AND LOVE OF CONVERSATION. SHE WAS A GREAT NEIGHBOR AND A
WONDERFUL HOST. THE DUNCAN NEWBURG ASSOCIATION
HOLIDAY PARTIES WILL NOT BE THE SAME WITHOUT HER AND I WILL
MISS SEEING HER THERE AND ELSEWHERE.
SHE IS SURVIVED BY STEPCHILDREN SHAYLA FROMER, KEVIN MOONEY
AND SIOBHAN STEVENS. NIECE CASEY NEWMAN.
SEVEN GRANDCHILDREN. EIGHT GREAT GRANDCHILDREN.
AND MANY FRIENDS AND RELATIVES AROUND THE WORLD.
WE SEND OUR CONDOLENCES TO HER FAMILY AND MANY FRIENDS.
REST IN PEACE, DIANA MOONEY. MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING.
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY
TO THE SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH.
>> ALONG WITH MY COLLEAGUE DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR SHERMAN
WALTON REGARDING BIRTH OUTCOMES AND DISPARITIES IN MATERNAL
HEALTH WE HAVE GREAT DISPARITIES IN OUR CITY WHEN IT
COMES TO BIRTH OUTCOMES. HEARTBREAKING, INEXCUSABLE
DISPARITIES. ALL BABIES AND THEIR MOMS
DESERVE A CHANCE TO THRIVE IN OUR CITY AND HAVE THE ACCESS
THAT THEY NEED TO RESOURCES TO ENSURE THEIR SUCCESS.
THIS IS THE ESSENCE OF EQUITY AND IT IS OUR MORAL IMPERATIVE.
OVER THE YEARS A BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SUPPORTED FUNDING
FOR MATERNAL HEALTH. >> DESPITE THAT WE ARE STILL
FALLING BEHIND OTHER COUNTIES. >> WE HAVE THE HIGHEST PRETERM
BIRTH RATE FOR CERTAIN POPULATIONS AND IN CERTAIN ZIP
CODES IN CALIFORNIA. WE WOULD LIKE A BETTER
UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT FUNDS WERE ALLOCATED AND EXPANDED.
I WAS ALSO DISMAYED TO LEARN FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD
STANDARD THAT THERE IS FUNDING ABOUT 800,000 THROUGH THE
STATE'S PRENATAL PRENATAL EQUITY INITIATIVE THAT WE ARE
SENDING BACK TO THE STATE AND THERE IS AT LEAST $8
MILLION IN UNDER SPENDING TO ADDRESS MATERNAL INEQUITIES.
THIS IS MORALLY INEXCUSABLE AND WE MUST ACT NOW.
LET'S CHERISH OUR BABIES. LET'S SUPPORT OUR MAMAS.
LET'S HOLD THIS DEPARTMENT ACCOUNTABLE FOR SETTING THE
FRAMEWORK FOR HEALTH EQUITY IN OUR CITY.
THIS IS A SOLVABLE PROBLEM. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. COLLEAGUES.
TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE TO SUPPORT THE
OPERATIONS OF OUR BELOVED MOVIE THEATERS CITYWIDE.
>> AS WE ALL KNOW, MOVIE THEATERS ARE ESSENTIAL PIECE OF
OUR CULTURAL FABRIC. >> THEY'RE COMMUNITY
CORNERSTONES GATHERING SPACES AND THEY SERVE A SPECIAL ROLE
IN BRINGING NEIGHBORHOODS TOGETHER TO CELEBRATE THE ARTS.
OUR FILM FESTIVALS SUCH AS FRAME LINE, THE WORLD'S LARGEST
LGBTQ PLUS FILM FESTIVAL AS A FILM AND OTHERS NOT ONLY
REFLECT THE STRENGTH OF SAN FRANCISCO'S DIVERSITY, THEY
ALSO GIVE UNIQUE OPPORTUNITIES FOR ARTISTS WHO ARE UNWELCOME
OR UNCELEBRATED ELSEWHERE. YET OVER THE PAST SEVERAL
DECADES MOVIE THEATERS HAVE BEEN THREATENED BY SHIFTING
STREAMING HABITS THE PANDEMICS AND MORE.
>> AND THE THEATERS HAVE BEEN HIT HARDEST BY THESE TOUGH
ECONOMIC CONDITIONS OR THE SMALL SINGLE SCREEN HISTORIC
THEATERS MANY OF WHICH WERE SMALL BUSINESSES AND BEEN
FORCED TO CLOSE IN RECENT YEARS .
NOW IN DISTRICT TWO WE HAVE A LANDMARK THEATER THE CLAY
THEATER THAT I'M VERY EXCITED TO SAY WILL BE THOUGHTFULLY
RESTORED AND WILL REOPEN AS A THEATER NEXT YEAR.
>> BUT WE ALSO KNOW THAT SERVING BEER AND WINE AT
THEATERS IS GOOD FOR THE BOTTOM LINE.
IT'S GOOD FOR LONG TERM HEALTH AND SUSTAINABILITY AS
BUSINESSES. AND WHEN I MET WITH THE PROJECT
SPONSORS AT THE CLAY THEATER THEY LET ME KNOW THAT OUR
PLANNING CODE TREATS MOVIE THEATERS WOULD LIKE TO SERVE
BEER AND WINE THE SAME AS RESTAURANTS AND WE LEVY THE
SAME PUNISHMENTS FOR NONCOMPLIANCE SPECIFICALLY
STATE LIQUOR LAWS MANDATE THAT MOVIE THEATERS WANT TO SERVE
BEER AND WINE, OPERATE A RESTAURANT IN CONJUNCTION
AND THEN OUR PLANNING CODE IMPLEMENTS THE SAME REVENUE
TEST ON THESE MOVIE THEATERS THAT WE PLACE ON RESTAURANTS
MEANING THAT THESE THEATERS WILL HAVE TO MAKE A MINIMUM OF
51% OF THEIR GROSS RECEIPTS FROM FOOD SALES PREPARED
AND SOLD TO GUESTS. SO IN PRACTICE WE ARE MANDATING
THAT ANY COMMUNITY THEATER ESPECIALLY THE NEWLY RENOVATED
CLAY THEATER SERVING BEER AND WINE MAKE AT LEAST 51% OF
THEIR REVENUE FROM FOOD THAT THEY PREPARE ON SITE
AND REGARDLESS HOW MUCH WE CHARGE FOR EXTRA BUTTER NO
AMOUNT OF POPCORN IS GOING TO MAKE 51% OF THEIR REVENUE.
THIS IS A TIME WHERE WE NEED TO MAKE IT EASIER TO INVEST IN AND
OPERATE THESE COMMUNITIES SPACES.
>> SO THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLAN AND GOES DEFINITION OF
MOVIE THEATER IN SECTION 102 TO ALLOW THEATERS TO PROVIDE
ONSITE BEER AND WINE FOR DRINKING ON PREMISES WITH AN
ABC LICENSE AND ONLY AS A MINOR AND INCIDENTAL USE.
WE NEED TO BE ENCOURAGING RESIDENTS TO GO TO THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD THEATER TO WALK THEIR LOCAL MERCHANT COURT OR
TO SUPPORT THE ARTS IN THIS CITY.
>> AND THIS LEGISLATION WILL MAKE IT CLEAR THAT MOVIE
THEATERS ARE NOT THE SAME AS RESTAURANTS.
AND OUR PLANNING CODE SHOULDN'T TREAT THEM THE SAME.
IT WILL MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE DOING WHAT WE CAN IN CITY HALL
TO BE A PARTNER AND A SUPPORTER OF OUR MOVIE THEATERS AND OF
THE ARTS. >> AND WHILE I'M PARTICULARLY
THRILLED TO STOP BY FOR A MOVIE AND ALSO POSSIBLY SOME SUNDAY
MORNING CARTOONS AT THE REOPEN CLAY THEATER IN THE COMING YEAR
OR SO, IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE FIX THIS ILLOGICAL REQUIREMENT
FOR ALL OUR THEATERS CITYWIDE TO BENEFIT BY ENACTING THIS
ORDINANCE WILL MAKE IT EASIER FOR ALL THEATERS BUT
PARTICULARLY OUR SMALL BUSINESSES, OUR LOCAL COMMUNITY
THEATERS TO CONTINUE TO OPERATE AS CHERISHED CULTURAL
CORNERSTONES. THANK YOU COLLEAGUES AND THEIR
ASSESSMENT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CHAIR. COLLEAGUES, FIRST I JUST WANT
TO ADD TO THE LETTER OF INQUIRY BY SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND JUST
STATE A REMINDER THAT IN 2020 SUPERVISOR FEWER ADDED $2
MILLION TO ADDRESS BLACK INFANT MORTALITY.
THERE WERE MANY REASONS WHY THIS WAS IMPORTANT AND TODAY WE
WOULD LIKE TO UNDERSTAND THE IMPACTS AND THE CHANGES THAT
HAVE TAKEN PLACE TO LOWER THESE NATIONAL STATISTICS.
WE WERE ALL IN RECEIPT OF A LETTER SIGNED BY DOCTORS
AND MEDICAL PROVIDERS DEDICATED TO SUPPORTING MATERNAL HEALTH
WHO ARE TELLING US THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS THE WORST BIRTH
DISPARITIES IN THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA.
BLACK MOTHERS REPRESENT ONLY 4% OF BIRTHS IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT
ACCOUNT FOR ABOUT 50% OF MATERNAL DEATHS WHICH IS FIVE
OUT OF TEN OVER THE LAST DECADE.
SO NEEDLESS TO SAY THIS IS A MAJOR PROBLEM AND WE WILL ALSO
BE HOSTING A HEARING ON THIS IN THE NEXT FEW MONTHS.
>> TODAY I'M ALSO FORMALLY REQUESTING A HEARING ON THE
UNITED STATES NAVY'S DELAYED DISCLOSURE OF AIRBORNE
PLUTONIUM DETECTED AT HUNTERS POINT SHIPYARD.
THE NAVY IDENTIFIED PLUTONIUM ABOVE THE ALLOWABLE LEVEL
IN NOVEMBER OF 2024 ON PARCEL G AND DID NOT REPORT IT TO THE
CITY UNTIL OCTOBER OF 2025. RECENTLY ALMOST A YEAR DELAY OF
NEARLY ONE YEAR FOR INFORMATION THAT DIRECTLY AFFECTS THE
PUBLIC HEALTH. >> THIS IS ABSOLUTELY
UNACCEPTABLE AND CANNOT BE EXCUSED OR MINIMIZE.
DISTRICT TEN IN THIS COMMUNITY HAS ENDURED DECADES OF BROKEN
PROMISES AND MISLEADING STATEMENTS AND DELAYED
DISCLOSURES FROM THE NAVY. THIS IS THE LATEST INCIDENT
THAT PROVES THAT THE NAVY CONTINUES TO HIDE INFORMATION
INSTEAD OF COMMUNICATING HONESTLY WITH THE BABY HUNTERS
POINT RESIDENTS AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> I AM REQUESTING THE US NAVY ,THE EPA, CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND THE SAN FRANCISCO
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO PROVIDE EVERY DOCUMENT, EVERY
TEST RESULT AND EVERY EXPLANATION FOR THIS FAILURE
AND TO OUTLINE WHAT PROTECTIONS IF ANY WERE IN PLACE DURING THE
11 MONTHS THE PUBLIC WAS KEPT IN THE DARK.
THE PEOPLE BEHIND THIS POINT DESERVE TRANSPARENCY, NOT MORE
EXCUSES. OUR OFFICE WILL CONTINUE TO
FIGHT FOR FULL ACCOUNTABILITY INDEPENDENT OVERSIGHT, FULL
CLEANUP TO PROTECT THE RESIDENTS WORKERS, THE PEOPLE
THAT LIVE AROUND AND THE ARTISTS ON THE SHIPYARD
AND COLLEAGUES. >> LAST I AM REQUESTING A
LETTER OF INQUIRY TO THE FOLLOWING DEPARTMENTS THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE, DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING SAN FRANCISCO, ALL MTA, SAN FRANCISCO PORT AND THE
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT ON WHY THEY CONTINUE
TO MAKE DECISIONS THAT OVERTLY BURDEN DISTRICT TEN
COMMUNITIES. RIGHT NOW THIS ADMINISTRATION
CONTINUES TO STRONG ARM THE DISTRICT TEN COMMUNITY AND IS
ENSURING THAT DISTRICT TEN IS SHOULDERING MANY OF THE HEAVY
BURDENS OF HOMELESSNESS AND OTHER ISSUES FOR THE CITY.
DISTRICT TEN CONTINUES TO CARRY MORE THAN OUR SHARE OF THE
CITY'S BURDENS. WE SHOW UP FOR SOLUTIONS BUT WE
SHOULD NOT HAVE TO BE USED TO SHOULDER ALL THE BURDENS.
TIME AND TIME AGAIN THE RV ENFORCEMENT PLAN WAS ENACTED ON
NOVEMBER 1ST AND NOW THE CITY IS PREPARING TO TOW PEOPLE'S
HOMES AND MOVE THEM TO PIER 68 IN DISTRICT TEN.
WITH THE COURT'S PERMISSION AND A SECRET DEAL THAT NO ONE
WAS AWARE WAS TAKING PLACE, THIS IS AN ATTEMPT TO QUIETLY
MOVE A SELF-CREATED PROBLEM INTO OUR COMMUNITY WITHOUT ANY
TRANSPARENCY OR ANY COMMUNITY INPUT WHATSOEVER.
>> THAT IS NOT STRATEGY. THAT IS DISPLACEMENT.
WE HAVE SEEN THIS PATTERN ALREADY.
>> TINY CABINS WERE SECRETLY MOVED FROM THE MISSION TO OUR
GERALD STREET SITE RECENTLY WITHOUT ANY COMMUNITY INPUT
AFTER PLANS FOR THE ORIGINAL SITE WERE CHANGED MULTIPLE
TIMES AGAIN WITHOUT COMMUNITY INPUT.
NOW THE CITY AT THE PUSHING OF MTA WANTS TO STORE TOWED RVS AT
PIER 68 WITH NO TRANSPARENCY, NO NOTICE AND NO RESPECT.
FAMILIES, SENIORS AND WORKING PEOPLE LIVE, WORK AND GATHER
AROUND THEIR. WE ARE NOT THE CITY STORAGE
YARD. WHEN OTHER COMMUNITIES DO NOT
WANT TO DEAL WITH HARD PROBLEMS IF THIS PLAN IS SAFE, EQUITABLE
AND EFFECTIVE THEN IT SHOULD BE SHARED ACROSS THE CITY AND NOT
DROPPED IN DISTRICT TEN AS A SECRET.
>> I'M CALLING FOR TRANSPARENCY, EQUITY AND REAL
HOUSING SOLUTIONS. SHOW US THE PLAN.
ENGAGE THE COMMUNITY. STOP CONCENTRATING THE CITY'S
BURDENS THAT CREATE NEGATIVE IMPACTS IN DISTRICT TEN.
JUST BECAUSE YOU DON'T CARE ABOUT THE FAMILIES, PEOPLE
AND COMMUNITIES IN THE SOUTHEAST SECTOR OF SAN
FRANCISCO, DISTRICT TEN WILL NOT BE THE CITY'S DUMPING
GROUND. >> TIME AFTER TIME I WANT TO
KNOW WHY THIS ADMINISTRATION IS BENT ON IGNORING D10
COMMUNITIES. I WANT THESE DEPARTMENTS TO
EXPLAIN WHY THEY FEEL THEY CAN IGNORE COMMUNITY VOICE
AND THEIR DECISION MAKING AND PUT ON RECORD WHAT THEY
HAVE AGAINST DISTRICT TEN AND HOW THEY MAKE THESE
DECISIONS. FURTHERMORE, S.F. MTA SHOULD BE
TRYING TO BRING COMMUNITIES TOGETHER AT A TIME WHEN THEY
ARE GOING TO BE ASKING THE VOTERS TO ADDRESS THEIR MANY
FISCAL ISSUES. IF S.F. MTA DOESN'T SUPPORT US,
WHY SHOULD WE SUPPORT THEM? >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
IF YOU LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER YOU
CAN SPEAK TO ITEMS 33 THROUGH 30 SIX WHICH ARE ON THE
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR AND OTHER
GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT MUST BE
WITHIN THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
>> WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER .
>> YES HI. SHORT LIVED WITH ROYAL BLUE
AND US THE SAME LIKE. >> COMING UP NEW KING OF FRANCE
. >> THE MISSION IS ACHIEVED
HERE. BEAUTY HAS NO NOTHING TO HIDE
SO I'M GOING TO GIVE YOU IN ADVANCE WHAT'S GOING TO BE
CIRCULATING ALL OVER THE CITY IN THE THOUSANDS.
>> SO YOU HEAD HEAD BREAK THE SILENCE OF INSTITUTIONALIZED
CHILD TRAFFICKING FROM THE ROOTS ON JONES ARE SOME
FRANCISCO BASED CIVIC FIRST COALITION TO PUT AN END TO THE
VERY CRIME LEADING TO NO FUTURE CALL ON THE ALL A GOVERNMENT
EARLY IMMEDIATELY INSTITUTIONAL TO MAINTAIN SILENCE EVIDENCING
BY ITSELF LONG TIME ORGANIZED WORLDWIDE OPERATIONS OF CHILD
TRAFFICKING SYSTEMATICALLY INCLUDING THE, TORTURING ORGAN
HARVESTING RITUAL SACRIFICING AND THE SMELL SMOLDERING OF ONE
TOO MANY CHILDREN EVERY DAY. >> IF IN THE US ALONE ONLY MAKE
YOUR VOICE AND PRESENCE A DUTY TO CALL OUT THE PEDOPHILIA
QUEENS RINGS AT THE BASE OF THIS WORST OF THE WORST IDEAS
AND SICKENING HUMAN ACTIVITY BY FROM THE SO-CALLED LEADERS AT
LARGE AND THEY ARE BLACK MALES DEPRAVED AND THEIR LOSSES PAST
THE WORLD FOR ACTION FEARLESSLY AROUND YOU BY COPYING OR
SHARING ON OR SHARING THIS LAW TO BETTER SHOW UP UNITED ON
IN GREAT NUMBERS AT CITY HALL AND TUESDAY FOR A START AHEAD
OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETINGS THAT USE THE PRESENT
HEAD OUT TO CREATE YOUR OWN DISPLAY SIGNS WITH THE FUTURE
IN YOUR HANDS FROM THIS POINT ON NOT FEEL THEIR EXCUSE LOADS
FOR NO HOPE YOURSELF YOU TELL FEEL AND TAKING CARE OF THE
CLAY I THINK YOU'RE IN TROUBLE .
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
OKAY IF ANYBODY HASN'T VOTED ON 50 SIR I'LL GIVE YOU SIR YOU
CANNOT SPEAK ABOUT VOTE IN THE CAMPAIGN TODAY MAINLY BECAUSE
GEORGE SOROS SAYS YES. BUT I'D LIKE TO READ FROM
PAUL'S EPISTLE IS BEFORE HE DIED WHEN A MAN GETS READY TO
DIE YOU OUGHT TO HANG ON HIS EVERY WORD.
ONLY LUKE IS WITH ME. TAKE MARK AND BRING HIM WITH
THE FOR HE IS PROFITABLE TO ME FOR THE MINISTRY AND TICKETS
HAVE I SENT TO EPHESUS THE CLOAK THAT I LEFT IT TROW US
WITH CARPETS WHEN NOW COME CHEMIST BRING WITH THE AND THE
BOOKS BUT ESPECIALLY THE PARCHMENTS ALEXANDER THE
COPPERSMITH DID ME MUCH EVIL THE LORD REWARD HIM ACCORDING
TO HIS WORKS OF WHOM BE THOU WHERE ALSO FOR HE HAS GREATLY
WITHSTOOD OUR WORDS AT MY FIRST ANSWER THIS IS BEFORE NERO KNOW
ME AND STOOD WITH ME BUT ALL MEN FORSOOK ME EVEN LUKE.
I PRAY GOD THAT IT MAY NOT BE LAID TO THEIR CHARGE
NOTWITHSTANDING THE LORD STOOD WITH ME AND STRENGTHENED ME
THAT BY ME THE PREACHING MIGHT BE FULLY KNOWN AND THAT ALL THE
GENTILES MIGHT HEAR AND I WAS DELIVERED OUT OF THE MOUTH OF
THE LION REFERRING TO NERO AS THE LION AND THE LORD SHALL
DELIVER ME FROM EVERY EVIL WORK AND WILL PRESERVE ME UNTO HIS
HEAVENLY KINGDOM TO WHOM BE GLORY FOREVER AND EVER.
AMEN. AND THEN HE WAS DECAPITATED.
NOW THIS THIS IS A PERFECT EXAMPLE OF HOW IF YOU'RE SAVED
YOU ARE SAVED BY GRACE NOT BY YOUR WORKS.
>> OKAY. THERE WASN'T ONE CHRISTIAN THAT
STOOD WITH PAUL, NOT ONE CHRISTIAN.
>> DOES THAT MEAN THERE WERE NOT CHRISTIANS OR WERE NOT
SAVED THAT THEY WERE GOING TO WITH THE REST OF THE WORLD THAT
REJECTED JESUS CHRIST? >> IT DOESN'T MEAN THAT IT
MEANS THAT ALL MEN ARE REALLY PATHETIC.
I MEAN REALLY AND YOU'RE ONLY SAVED BY GRACE.
YOU KNOW, YOU REALLY YOU'RE IF YOU'RE NOT SAVED BY GRACE THEN
EVERYONE'S GOING TO. >> OH, RIGHT.
>> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE LET HIM KNOW THAT YES, WE'LL COME
COLLECT THAT FROM YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOUGHT A SUPERVISORS FOR THE RECORD MY NAME IS CHRISTOPHER
KLEIN. I ALSO GO BY SERGEANT KLEIN OF
THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS. AND WHEN I FIRST GOT OUT OF THE
MARINE CORPS I WENT TO NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY
AND IT'S ONE OF THE LARGEST UNIVERSITIES IN THE UNITED
STATES. THEY ALSO DO RESEARCH.
SO EVERYTHING THAT I'M SHARING WITH YOU IS THROUGH RESEARCH ON
INVESTIGATE OF SKILLS A BACHELOR OF SCIENCE OF
INVESTIGATION AND WE ARE IN A VERY TROUBLING TIME A 100 YEAR
WAR BASICALLY AND IT'S BASICALLY EVERY UNIVERSITY
IN SAN FRANCISCO PUT PEOPLE ON RESEARCH AND IT'S UNETHICAL.
WE HAVE THE PROOF WE GAVE IT TO THE SHERIFF.
PLEASE USE YOUR VOICE TO GET THE SHERIFF TO MOVE ON.
THREE PEOPLE THAT WE'VE IDENTIFIED AND THOSE PEOPLE ARE
MATT HANEY, RAM COPPOCK AND MATTHEW JOHNS.
THERE ARE OTHER PEOPLE THAT ARE CULPABLE AND ARE AWARE OF THIS
. HOWEVER, THOSE THREE PEOPLE ARE
THE MOST CULPABLE AND WE'RE ASKING THE SHERIFF TO MOVE FOR
AN ARRESTING MATT HANEY. AND WE KNOW IT'S DIFFICULT
BECAUSE HE HAS A FRIENDSHIP WITH THEM.
BUT AGAIN, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HERE DO YOU HAVE
THAT REPORT IF YOU NEED ANOTHER COPY OF THAT REPORT, I CAN
FORWARD IT TO YOU. BUT WE NEED EVERYONE IN THIS
ROOM TO UNDERSTAND WHAT THE BELMONT REPORT IS AND THIS WAS
CREATED BECAUSE OF SAN FRANCISCO IN 1978.
THIS REPORT WAS ON THE BELMONT REPORT.
I WAS CREATED IN 1979. I HAD TO GO BACK IN THE MARINE
CORPS FOR SAFETY AND SECURITY BECAUSE I WAS EDUCATING PEOPLE
ABOUT THIS. THAT'S HOW SERIOUS IT IS.
PEOPLE ARE DYING ON YOUR STREETS AND THAT'S WHY THE
MILITARY WAS GOING TO BE CALLED IN AND JUST TO BE VERY CLEAR,
THE MARINE CORPS, THE ARMY, THE NAVY AND THE AIR FORCE CAN COME
IN AT ANY TIME WHEN THERE ARE HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS
HAPPENING ON YOUR WATCH. SO PLEASE GET WITH THE SHERIFF.
PLEASE MOVE ON THIS RIGHT AWAY. AND AGAIN IT'S MATT HANEY, RON
CO-PACKER AND MATTHEW JOHNS. AND IF IT'S NOT DONE SOONER WE
WILL ADD PEOPLE TO THE LIST. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. THANK SPEAKER BOARD PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT AND BOARD MEMBERS. MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON
. >> I'M STILL VERY DISTURBED
ABOUT THE APPARENT USE OF THE MAYOR OF A PERSONAL COMPUTER
THAT IS NOW GOING TO BECOME THE OFFICIAL GOVERNMENT COMPUTER OF
SAN FRANCISCO. I THINK THAT THIS IS DANGEROUS
BECAUSE HE CAN THEN MANIPULATE WHAT IS BEING RELEASED TO THE
PUBLIC AND FOR EXAMPLE, I'M DRESSED LIKE THIS BECAUSE NEXT
SUMMER IS 60 YEARS FOR THE SUMMER OF LOVE.
THAT WAS IN 1967. >> I CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO
IN 64 AS AN ADULT AND HAVE LIVED HERE EVER SINCE, HAVE
MADE MY PROFESSION HERE AND IN FEDERAL COURTS AND I HAVE NEVER
QUITE SEEN THE EXCEPT FOR MAYBE OUR PRESIDENT TO GRAB A POWER
THAT THE MAYOR IS NOW GRABBING A AND I HEAR THAT THE WEST SIDE
IS UP IN ALARM AND WELL THEY SHOULD BE BECAUSE THE
MAYOR WANTS TO PUT THROUGH A TAX POLICY THAT FAVORS THE
DOWNTOWN INSTEAD OF THE PEOPLE OUT IN THE WEST SIDE DISTRICT
AND DISTRICT FOUR AND FIVE. I BELIEVE IT IS AND THE
COMPUTER WILL BE ABLE TO DETERMINE THINGS LIKE HOW MANY
PARCELS ARE OUT THERE. WELL WE CAN GET THAT RIGHT NOW
BUT HOW MANY PEOPLE HAVE CHILDREN IN THE WEST SIDE
VERSUS DOWNTOWN AREAS? AND THAT'S VERY IMPORTANT
BECAUSE FOR EXAMPLE, MAYBE IN DISTRICT EIGHT WE OUGHT TO
LOOK TO ART TO BE LOOKING NEXT ELECTION FOR A STRAIGHT
IN DISTRICT EIGHT AND MAYBE CHILDREN SHOULD BE IDENTIFIED
IN POPULATIONS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD GRIFFIN
LEE HERE AT DISTRICT TO RESIDENT AND STAFF I CONNECT
THEIR STAFF HERE FOR A COUPLE DIFFERENT REASONS.
ONE I WOULD LIKE TO ENCOURAGE THE BOARD BASED OFF OF MEMBER
FEEDBACK TO LOOK INTO CHANGING SOME OF THE DESIGN AND PROPOSE
PLANS FOR THE INNER SUNSET TRANSPORTATION STUDY THAT IS
PART OF DISTRICT SEVEN SPECIFICALLY WE HAVE A LOT OF
MEMBERS CONCERNED ABOUT THE BIKE INFRASTRUCTURE BEING
PROPOSED ON SEVENTH AVENUE AND AS AN ALTERNATIVE SOLUTION
OUR MEMBERS HAVE SUGGESTED POTENTIALLY CONSIDERING A BIKE
PROTECTED LANE ON EITHER FIFTH, SIXTH OR NINTH AVENUE.
>> THE REASON FOR THAT SPECIFICALLY IS BECAUSE WHEN
YOU'RE GOING WEST ON LINCOLN WAY TURNING ON SEVENTH IT'S ONE
OF THE ONLY OPTIONS TO TURN LEFT WITH A DESIGNATED LEFT
ARROW. FURTHERMORE, SEVENTH FIVE IS A
MAJOR THOROUGHFARE THERE FOR COMMUTERS COMING FROM THE EAST
SIDE. >> GETTING BACK TO THE GREEN
HONDA FOR US ETC. SECONDLY, I WOULD LIKE TO URGE THE BOARD TO
LOOK INTO POTENTIAL RELIEF OR SOLUTIONS TO SUPPORT SMALL
BUSINESSES ALONG THE GEARY CORRIDOR WHERE THE SEWAGE
PROJECT IS TAKING PLACE RIGHT NOW.
I THINK IT'S A TWO YEAR PROJECT AND SMALL BUSINESSES ARE
HURTING IN THAT AREA RIGHT NOW AT THIS IS DIRECT FEEDBACK I'VE
HAD FROM CONVERSATIONS OVER THE LAST WEEK LASTLY NOT ON BEHALF
OF NECESSARILY CONNECTED THAT BUT I URGE THE BOARD TO
CONSIDER SOLUTIONS ALTHOUGH I DO AND WE DO SUPPORT RECOVERY
FIRST AND ABSTINENCE BASED SOLUTIONS I STILL THINK THE
CITY OWNS LOG CABIN RANCH AND I KNOW THAT MIGHT BE A LONGER
TERM PLAY BUT IT COULD BE A SOLUTION TO GET THOSE THAT NEED
SERVICES AND SHELTER IN AN ISOLATED AREA TO GET THEM BACK
ON TRACK. >> LASTLY, THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS I THINK SPEAKER WELCOME BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
AND MAYOR OFFERS A SAN FRANCISCO THE TITLE OF MY
SPEECH TODAY IS ARE YOU A WOLF OR A SHEEP?
>> WHEN I WAS THREE I BROKE MY ARM.
I SET MY MOM INTO A FRENZY OF CHAOS AND A TOPSY TURVY ROAD TO
MOTHERHOOD. I WAS ONLY THREE YEARS OLD BACK
THEN. MY MOM SAID WE WERE GOING TO A
HOUSEBOAT FOR DINNER OF ECSTASY.
I CLIMBED THE LADDER OF A FACE FOR FORWARD MY BACK TOWARD THE
STEPS OF TEARS OF TWO HANDS HOLDING THE LADDER.
I WAS STUCK IN A THIRD STEP UNABLE TO GET OUT PREDICAMENT I
JUMP AND SCREAM AND LUCKILY THEY HIT THE FLOOR.
MY MOM HAD TO CANCEL ALL HER PLANS.
SHE CALLED A BEST DOCTOR TO LOCK TWO ARMED WITH SPLINTERS.
TO THIS DAY MY ARM WAS CROOKED. WORSE IT CAUSED SO MUCH AGONY
FOR MINE FOR YEARS TO COME. MY MOM ALWAYS GAVE ME THE WORLD
TO ME WHEN I WAS GOING TO SCHOOL AT AGE THREE SHE HIRED
SOMEONE TO STAND IN FRONT OF A SCHOOLYARD SO I WON'T CRY.
THE IMAGE OF HER HIDING A PERSON OUT TO WATCH ME OVER
ETCHED INTO MY HEAD. ALTHOUGH I HAVE ALWAYS
RESPECTED TEACHERS IT WAS MY MOM WHO GAVE THE WORLD
KINDNESS, COMPASSION AND POWERFUL IMAGE AS MY MOM.
MY MOM PASSED AWAY IN MARCH OF 2021 I CONFRONTED MAGGIE WONG
TO SEE MY MOM BEFORE SHE TOOK HER LAST BREATH.
MAGGIE WONG MS. CHINATOWN OF 2018 ALSO MISSED POPULARITY OF
MS.. CHINESE INTERNATIONAL 2019 FOR
MAGGIE SHE DID ALL SHE HAD DONE GAINING HER CROWN AND SEE MY
MOM GO WAS AS GOOD AS IT GETS BUT NOT FOR ME IN 2022.
BUT LISTEN TO JOE ROGAN DUDE I GOT ONE INVITE TO MY PODCAST
AND WITH THAT I DECIDED TO CREATE A WORLDWIDE CONSTITUTION
FOR JOE BIDEN. THE LIST OF FOUR AXIS OF FEMALE
SUPERPOWER HAS GROWN TO 28 SINCE THEN.
I IS ALL IN A DAY'S WORK. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> MY NAME IS W R DUFFY
TENDERLOIN NEIGHBORHOOD ACTIVIST TODAY IS KIND OF THE
HIGH HOLY DAY FOR NEIGHBORHOOD ACTIVISTS.
THE ELECTION DAY WHENEVER THEY FALL I WE WORK DILIGENTLY TO
SUPPORT ONE SIDE OR ANOTHER OF VARIOUS THINGS AND IT'S A
WONDERFUL THING THAT WHATEVER THE VOTERS VOTE FOR THAT'S WHAT
WE GO FOR. >> THAT'S WHERE WE GO WITH I
WOULD SAY THAT I FALL A LITTLE BIT CLOSER TO THE MISHEAR
PASCAL'S BELIEFS THAN I DO TO THE CHRISTIAN GUY.
>> WELL, WE CERTAINLY GOT A WIDE RANGE OF BELIEFS HERE
TODAY AT THE PUBLIC COMMENT AND ONE THING I GUESS IT'S NOT
TOO UNSURPRISING THAT EVERYONE THEY'VE TALKED AGREED WITH IS
THAT WE'RE IN A BIT OF TROUBLE. WE'RE IN A DARK SPOT NOW I'D
LIKE TO POINT OUT THAT POLITICAL SWINGS OVER U.S.
HISTORY THEY'VE TEND TO BE IN THIS 60 TO 75 YEAR RANGE
LIKE FOR INSTANCE, THE DEMOCRATIC REPUBLICAN PARTY WAS
THE ONLY DOMINANT PARTY FOR ABOUT THAT LENGTH OF TIME
BEFORE THE REPUBLICANS CAME IN AND THE DEMOCRATS HAVE BEEN
WERE THE DOMINANT PARTY FROM 1930 TO ABOUT 1990 ABOUT 60
YEARS. SO SINCE REAGAN AND THE
CONGRESS STARTED TO TURN REPUBLICAN, THAT WAS, YOU KNOW,
AROUND 1990 THAT WAS ABOUT 40 YEARS AGO, 30, 35 YEARS AGO.
>> SO IF HOWEVER TODAY TURNS OUT IF THIS IS THE BOTTOM IF
THIS IS THE BOTTOM AND WE CAN START MOVING TO A BETTER PLACE,
THEN WE HAVE WE'LL HAVE DODGED A CALAMITY WORSE THAN JIM CROW,
VIETNAM, THE COVID SHUTDOWN, THE 28 RECESSION, HURRICANE
KATRINA, THE AIDS CRISIS AND JONESTOWN COMBINED AND I
COULD THROW IN MILK AND MOSCONI AND PROP 13 AND MANY OTHER
THINGS IF THIS IS THE BOTTOM WE WILL BE VERY LUCKY I BESEECH
PROVIDENCE THAT THAT BE THE CASE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> NEXT SPEAKER A SPEAKER I WANT TO SUBMIT THIS PICTURE
HERE. I WANT TO SUBMIT THIS I WANT TO
ASK WORK A PUZZLE WILL COME COLLECT THAT FROM YOU.
YES I WANT THAT FOR A PUBLIC AND IF YOU COULD PLEASE APPLY
AND THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
RIGHT NOW I'M SPEAKING TO YOU RIGHT NOW.
MAN THEY ARE TRYING TO FORCED ME OUT OF MY PLACE RIGHT NOW
BUT I HAVE SOME DAMAGES DONE TO MY APARTMENT AND THEY ARE
REFUSING TO FIX IT AND OTHERWISE INSTEAD OF
PREPARING WHAT THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO BE REPAIRING THEY ARE
FORCING ME OUT AT THE STRIP THAT I GAVE YOU ON THE SECOND
STEP THEY ARE CHARGING ME FOR PROPERTY DAMAGE IF YOU CAN SEE
THIS PICTURE WITH YOU PUT THIS PICTURE UP SO EVERYBODY CAN SEE
YOU HAVE TV PLEASE WE SAY NOW YEAH I'M ASKING FOR A PUBLIC
HEARING ON SUBMITTED WHAT I I SUBMIT TO YOU BECAUSE RIGHT NOW
EACH STATE IS DISCUSSING WHETHER THEY WILL LET ME STAY
IN THE PROGRAM OR OUT OF THE PROGRAM BEHIND THIS RIGHT HERE.
I ALSO HAVE PRESENTED TO YOU OF A MEDICAL RECORD WHEN I FELL
DOWN INSIDE OF MY HOUSE AND HIT MY HEAD AND I WAS TRANSFERRED
TO THE HOSPITAL, THIS IS RETALIATION ON ME.
THEY RAISE MY BILL FROM 2001 70 TO 5054 SO I'M ACTUALLY YOU FOR
PUBLIC HEARING YOU SEE MY HOUSE.
CAN I GET A PUBLIC HEARING? SIR, THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY
TO TELL US WHAT YOU'D LIKE THE BOARD TO HEAR.
>> WHAT MY MY MY POINT IS, MA'AM AND I'VE BEEN IN A
PROGRAM ONCE BEFORE STANDING IN FRONT OF YOU.
>> I HAVE A VERY BAD HEAD INJURY.
THE PROPERTY MANAGER CALLS IN THIS THING AND THIS IS THE
SECOND TIME THE FIRST TIME I WAS STANDING IN FRONT OF YOU I
WAS IN A PROGRAM I HAD JUST AS IN MY I AND ON TOP OF MY HEAD
THIS IS A NEW PROGRAM RIGHT HERE.
I'M IN I'M BEING FORCED OUT OF MY PLACE AS I SPEAK TO YOU NOW
I'M COMING TO YOU AGAIN FOR PUBLIC HEARING BASED ON THIS I
HAVE A A $1,700 MEDICAL BILL. MY INSURANCE IS NOT GOING TO
PAY IT. I WANT TO CHARGE IT TO THE
CHINESE. >> PLEASE.
THE MANAGER. >> I WANT HIM BE SO SIR, IF
YOU'LL JUST WAIT AT THE PODIUM, WE'LL COME AROUND AND WE HAVE
YOUR PAPERWORK. WE'LL TALK FURTHER WITH YOU.
I CANNOT PROMISE YOU A HEARING .
I WANT MY TIME. I CAN.
THANK YOU, SIR. >> YOUR YOUR TIME'S CONCLUDED
AND I'M ASKING FOR OPEN THE DOOR.
>> YES, PLEASE. IF YOU WOULDN'T MIND WAITING
FOR US. THANK YOU.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO'D LIKE TO
ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED, MADAM CLERK.
LET'S CALL THE REMAINING THE REMAINING ITEMS ON THE FLOOR
ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 33
THROUGH 36 ITEM 33 THROUGH 36 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE AND I DON'T SEE ANYBODY PUTTING
THEIR NAME IN THE QUEUE TO SEVER ANYTHING.
SO MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
33 THROUGH 36 SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDEL
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
I HAVE NONE TO REPORT. MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE
READ THE IN MEMORIAM? >> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN FOR THE LATE MR. GARY
MCLANE ALSO KNOWN AS EMPRESS MALINA AND MS..
DIANA MOONEY ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR THE
BELOVED FELINE KNOWN AS KITTY CAT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE
END OF OUR AGENDA. DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS
BEFORE US TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY AND WE ARE ADJOURNED